<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Leonardo Bertini &#8211; 4D-REEF</title>
	<atom:link href="/4D-REEF/tag/leonardo-bertini/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/4D-REEF/</link>
	<description>Past, present, and future of  coral reefs in the Coral Triangle</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 14:31:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>4D-Reef at the 15th International Coral Reef Symposium</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/4d-reef-at-the-15th-international-coral-reef-symposium/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 13:18:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fursman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3697</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Where do we even begin, it's the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where do we even begin, it&#8217;s the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog post. (For those clueless about our awful joke see Fig. 1c; self-explanatory hopefully &#x1f605;?). This event was also the first ever climate neutral ICRS. Anyway, strap in and prepare to hear about how we schooled (another reef joke!!) for a week with fellow reef enthusiasts in the charming city of Bremen, northern Germany.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3708 " src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png" alt="" width="382" height="554" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-200x290.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-207x300.png 207w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-400x579.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-600x869.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png 707w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-768x1112.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1: <strong>a):</strong> The “Town Musicians of Bremen” &#8211; a Grimm’s fairy tale about a group of aging animals who move to Bremen to become musicians and their stack is an unofficial symbol of the city. <strong>b): </strong>The opening ceremony of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS. <strong>c)</strong> A blue-spotted cornet fish (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fistularia_commersonii">Fistularia commersonii)</a>.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>ICRS usually happens every four years and, after the 2021 edition was turned into a virtual meeting due to the pandemic, the wilds of humanity descended upon the delayed in-person event in order to (while following all health and safety protocols) socialise and discuss all things reef! This cosmopolitan single event had more than 1500 attendees coming from more than 170 countries across the globe, joining online and in-person. 4D-Reef was well represented, coming from across Europe to join with our endemic Bremenites who were helping to organise the event.</p>
<p>Those Bremen-based 4D-Reefers present were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Daniel Schürholz (Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Arjun Chennu (Max-Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Estradivari (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Sebastian Ferse (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Kathrine Maxwell (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
</ul>
<p>Honestly, each one of them deserves their own round of applause and their own blog post for that matter, as they have been central to the organisation and success of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS and all behind-the-scenes perks. To all the Bremen 4D-Reefers, we would like to express our gratitude and admiration on behalf of all our colleagues. They have gone to extreme lengths, chaired sessions, organised side events, led visits to their institutes and on top of all that also presented their own research at ICRS. Hats off to you guys!!</p>
<p>The 4D reef delegation was not just composed of endemic folks. We had a significant representation of 4D-Reefers from all over the place who made their way to Bremen to give either poster or oral presentations (check the official tweet from 4D-Reef and the various threads for more deets and super dooper sciency pics and embarrassing moments too &#8211; yeah there was a party in the end and yeah we shook it all off till we bleached). As part of the visiting delegation, we had:</p>
<ul>
<li>Leo Bertini (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Bristol)</li>
<li>Max Fursman (Goethe University Frankfurt)</li>
<li>Andrew Torres (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
<li>Kenneth Johnson (The Natural History Museum)</li>
<li>Erica Hendy (University of Bristol)</li>
<li>William Harrison (Naturalis Biodiversity Centre &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
</ul>
<p>If you&#8217;d like to have a glimpse at what each of them have been up to, please check out the <a href="https://www.icrs2022.de/fileadmin/user_upload/ICRS2022_BookOfAbstracts_July2.pdf">Official Conference Book of Abstracts</a> by searching their names.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3721 size-fusion-800" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png" alt="" width="800" height="405" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-200x101.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-300x152.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-400x203.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-540x272.png 540w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-600x304.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-768x389.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2: All the 4D-Reef PhDs hard at work, presenting posters, talks and their equipment.</em><br />
<em><strong><u>Top row</u></strong><u>:</u>  <strong>Daniel</strong> proudly stands next to his Hyper Diver holding up the information posters, waiting to ambush anyone passing by and tell them all about the wonderous imaging that can be done.<strong> Andrew</strong> gleefully discusses his work at his poster during the poster sessions, enthralling a passer-by with his knowledge. <strong><u>Middle row</u></strong>:<strong> Kat</strong> dazzles the crowd with her talk on coral reef terraces, scattering pictures of her fieldwork in the Philippines throughout to make us jealous! <strong>Estra </strong>educates everyone on MPAs and the emergence of OECMs and their benefits. <strong>Max </strong>doesn’t clam up as he discusses Tridacna shell chemistry! <strong><u>Bottom row</u></strong>: <strong>Leo </strong>has captured a CT lover and is busy discussing the ins and outs of coral scanning. <strong>Will </strong>wows those nearby with his remarks on changing coral reef habitats.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Face to face is important: strengthening connections and accelerating collabs</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a fantastic opportunity for us to present our work to the reef community, and many of the 4D-Reefers had posters and talks at the conference. It was such a nice change of pace to be able to chat to people face to face about science and answer questions from them over a second glass of wine or third bagel. Some of us got to meet up with colleagues from previous endeavours, be it our masters or other research projects. But more importantly got to meet new people, discuss new ideas for research and potential collaborations. We were able to expand our network through our current peers, including friends we’ve been working in close collaboration with from Cardiff University, Imperial College London, Malaysia, Singapore and Frankfurt, as they acted as match makers and introduced us to their own networks.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3710 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png" alt="" width="566" height="471" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-200x167.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-300x250.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-600x500.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-768x640.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-800x666.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3: Leo reuniting with and meeting new people.<strong> a)</strong> Dear friends Catie, Dom Brown and Luigi whom I worked with during my MSc looking at how reefs in Chagos have endured since the 2015 mass bleaching event. <strong>b)</strong> A fellow Brazilian ICRS attendee, Gabriel Cardoso, a PhD at Frei University Berlin looking at coral geochemical records. I met Gabriel in person after having read from his latest and outstanding work investigating how reefs in the Abrolhos bank were impacted by turbidity caused by mining refuse following the collapse of the Fundão dam, considered the biggest environmental disaster in Brazilian history, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969721059581">more here</a>. <strong>c) </strong>A prosecco with Sara Todorovic by my poster. Sara and her supervisor Dr Henry Wu, from ZMT, have been my collaborators. They look at geochemical signatures in coral cores from which I am automating the retrieval of growth rates and coral endobiont metrics.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3711 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png" alt="" width="560" height="563" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-200x201.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-600x603.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-768x772.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4: Social gatherings. <strong>a and</strong> <strong>d) </strong>The members of 4D-Reef and associates gathered for a beer and food after a hard day of conferencing! <strong>b)</strong> Allia Rosedy, our Malaysian associate, munching on a pretzel tree. <strong>c)</strong> Polyp Leo overheating and expelling his zooxanthellae while showing his moves to the beat of ABBA. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>The first climate neutral ICRS ever</strong><br />
Given how our reefs have been suffering in the face of anthropogenic pressures, the least we can do to halt global warming is to try and minimize our everyday carbon footprints and this was the mindset behind every single aspect of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS.</p>
<p>For instance, attendees were given free public transport around town, thus encouraging a greener way of mass mobility (our badges acted as public transport passes – how clever of you people!). When it comes to food during either coffee breaks or lunches, catering was also well thought-out and vegetarian (we, being a Brazilian and an Irish, were suspicious of this, given our white-tip-shark-like instincts for blood – another reef joke, it’s been a while). But honestly, food was so outstandingly tasty that we welcomed the menu like sea anemones welcome clown fish.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-fusion-200 wp-image-3712 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="141" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-300x212.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-400x283.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-600x424.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-768x543.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-800x565.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 5: Post-lunch break in the ICRS poster lounge. That was the best place to chill and recover from our food comas after lunch (left to right: Max, Leo and Andrew- not so satiated apparently?).</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Another striking aspect from catering was that priority was given for seasonal and local produce and the next day’s menu included ingredients used the day before to reduce food waste. Speaking of waste, this year there was rarely a flyer or physical promotional goodies around (let’s be honest those often end up forgotten in drawers). The entire programme was available to attendees via a web application, with real time announcements, chat, polling, and social functionalities. Attendees were also encouraged to bring their own liquid containers for drinking water and paper cups were offered as a better alternative to plastic.</p>
<p>Of course, it is impossible to actively reduce our carbon footprint to zero over such a short amount of time. There were energy costs for ventilating the venue, electricity, participant overseas travel emissions and other essentials that we cannot give up on (after all, we will never be as resourceful and energy efficient as corals). For this, organisers used part of the fees to purchase carbon credits equivalent of 1.491 tons of carbon emissions. The purchase is regulated by a third company who ensures measures are put into place to neutralize our carbon footprints following the UN environment programme and the Kyoto protocol.</p>
<p><strong>Our retrospective</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a wonderful opportunity to not only showcase the incredible work we’ve been doing as part of 4D-Reef and to bring awareness of how important turbid reefs are, but also to get new perspectives and connect with an amazing swarm of both young and well-established scientists from across multiple fields.</p>
<p>The conference was an opportunity to celebrate our endurance over the hardship the pandemic has brought onto the community, both as a whole and for some at deeply personal levels. Throughout the event, we shared (and vented – because we’re all human) about how we managed to stay afloat through such murky times. There was a moment to remember all the loved ones we lost along the way since the last in-person ICRS. May we continue their legacy and make the remaining reefs proud of what we do to protect the oceans!</p>
<p>The 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS has definitely set the bar high for any upcoming conferences. We already look forward to the ingenuity that will come with the 16<sup>th</sup> ICRS, which will be in New Zealand (i.e., land of Erica, land of the kiwis and the Maori).</p>
<p>Ka kite ano, ICRS!</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Max-Fursman-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2743"><span class="esr-link">Max Fursman</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy and Biodiversity</p>
	<p>Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some interesting samples from the Leiden collections</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/leo-samples-naturalis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 10:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3376</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London) I had a closer look at some of the samples that Prof. Willem Renema’s team from Naturalis sorted for me. Without doing any analyses or anything, there were already so many clues about how the conditions were in oceans 200 years ago and how these corals were]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London)</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I had a closer look at some of the samples that Prof. Willem Renema’s team from Naturalis sorted for me. Without doing any analyses or anything, there were already so many clues about how the conditions were in oceans 200 years ago and how these corals were growing, which is very exciting!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the samples I mentioned in the <a href="/4D-REEF/remote-collaborations-with-naturalis-biodiversity-center/">previous blog post</a> was a sample which showed high rates of bio-erosion or ‘endobiotic occupation’ (sample 1 on Figure 2 below). This is likely a result from Christmas tree worms, often very colourful and exotic! The name Christmas tree worm does not derive from its ecology but more its appearance of brightly coloured crowns that radiate a tube-like body, essentially looking like a Christmas tree! These worms are sedentary, so they often find a place, such as on a coral and don’t move around much from that area.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3378" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Christmas-tree-worms.jpg" alt="" width="503" height="307" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Christmas-tree-worms-200x122.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Christmas-tree-worms-300x183.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Christmas-tree-worms-400x244.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Christmas-tree-worms.jpg 503w" sizes="(max-width: 503px) 100vw, 503px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 1: Close-up of a Christmas tree worm anchored in a coral with it&#8217;s crowns exposed. Source: https://commons.wikimedia.org/</span></p>
<p><em><strong>An interesting relationship</strong></em><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">We believe though that the term bio-erosion in this case is not really the appropriate and accurate term to give to this interaction between the coral and the Christmas tree worm, as bio-erosion suggests that the effects are detrimental. In this case, we prefer to use the term endobiota as the Christmas tree worm is not causing a detrimental effect on the coral as it may have been removing the sediment from the top of the coral while also aiding in the coral’s nutrition. In fact, many coral endobionts, such and endolithic algae and sponges, can actually be important for corals, especially in times when the coral is bleaching as they can provide important additional nutritional sources and give the corals an upper hand to welcome new zooxanthellae when recovering from bleaching events.</span></p>
<p><em><strong>What&#8217;s in a shape?</strong></em><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Another interesting observation from my set of samples (Figure 2), is that the sample indicated by number 1 in the photo is very spherical in shape compared to number 2, which is very bumpy. The spherical shape suggests that light and sediment conditions were very homogeneous and so the growth of the coral is homogeneous. Lumpy corals (such as specimen 2 in the photo) suggest that there were differences in environmental conditions such as light availability or sedimentation which led to different growth rates in different parts of the coral. Additionally, when a coral is bumpy, sediment accumulates in the crevices a lot more than in spherical corals so this gives us a lot of information on the conditions in which the coral was living and the different strategies they adopted in order to grow in different environments.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3371" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2.png" alt="" width="307" height="410" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2-200x267.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2-225x300.png 225w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2.png 307w" sizes="(max-width: 307px) 100vw, 307px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 2: Set of massive </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Porites</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> specimens from the Naturalis collection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is so interesting that just by looking at these historical specimens you can already decipher a lot about the conditions that these corals were living in, giving us important information on how the oceans were 200 years ago! Looking at these specimens from Naturalis has already been incredibly exciting and I hope to unravel some more interesting facts about the history of these corals in the next blogposts to come! </span></p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Remote collaborations with Naturalis Biodiversity Center</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/leo-remote-collaborations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 08:56:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3367</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London) Since being in lockdown, the Natural History Museum London has continued to work with our partner institutions and collaborators. The pandemic hasn’t stopped us from working internationally! In my research, we collaborate with Prof. Willem Renema and his team from Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden. Having]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London)</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since being in lockdown, the Natural History Museum London has continued to work with our partner institutions and collaborators. The pandemic hasn’t stopped us from working internationally! In my research, we collaborate with Prof. Willem Renema and his team from Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden. Having this collaboration means we can share the specimens from our collections to increase our sample sizes. The Naturalis collection houses many coral specimens from turbid sites in the Coral Triangle, some of the oldest ones were collected during historic expeditions such as the Sibellius and the Siboga expeditions. Given my research is focussing on Indonesian corals, the Siboga expedition is incredibly significant.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Max Carl Wilherm Weber, German-Dutch zoologist and bio-geographer, led the Siboga expedition in 1899 to 1900. The expedition was a zoological and hydrographical expedition to Indonesia, and some of the sites are the ones we are still exploring today! The Indonesian Archipelago is home to over 17,000 islands rich in flora and fauna, especially coral reefs and has a great abundance of marine life.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3369" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route.png" alt="" width="557" height="391" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-200x140.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-300x210.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-400x281.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-600x421.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-768x539.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-800x561.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-1024x718.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route-1200x842.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Siboga-route.png 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 557px) 100vw, 557px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 1: Route of the Siboga expedition (1899-1900) with the red star indicating the main 4D-REEF study area, Spermonde Archipelago. Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siboga_expedition</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Weber appointed a crew of seven scientists to join him on the expedition. He even asked his wife, Anna Antoinette Weber-van Bosse (feature image, top row, third from the left), a Dutch phycologist specialising in marine algae to join. Even this was groundbreaking as it was not common at the time for women scientists to go on expeditions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During the expedition, they collected a number of specimens from all different animal and plant groups. These included some of the coral specimens present at Naturalis, which are part of my study! It is so exciting to work with specimens that have so much historical significance behind them!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The samples that our collaborators at Naturalis sorted out for me were very varied! One (1 in the photo below) showed very high rates of ‘bio-erosion’/occupation, likely from the Christmas tree worms, however its shape is very spherical and homogeneous. Other samples, such as 2 in the photo, had very bumpy shapes and were not spherical at all. It was very exciting to have such a variety of samples, as this would give us so much information as what the conditions were in the oceans 200 years ago!</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3371" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2.png" alt="" width="307" height="410" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2-200x267.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2-225x300.png 225w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_Leiden-samples2.png 307w" sizes="(max-width: 307px) 100vw, 307px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 2: Set of massive </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Porites</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> specimens from the Naturalis collection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We thank our collaborators from Naturalis, especially Prof. Willem Renema and his team, for continuing our partnership and sorting through their collections to add to my research. Despite us not being able to travel to their collections and meet in person, we are still working stronger than ever and overcoming the obstacles of this pandemic. I hope that I will be able to travel to Leiden to thank them all in person!  </span></p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>My first day back at the NHM Collections</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/leo-nhm-collections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 08:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3354</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London) After many months of working from home, I was very excited to get to visit the Natural History Museum (NHM) collections to look at some specimens for my research. This was my first time back to the NHM Coral Collection and even though you cannot see]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London)</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After many months of working from home, I was very excited to get to visit the Natural History Museum (NHM) collections to look at some specimens for my research. This was my first time back to the NHM Coral Collection and even though you cannot see my whole face because of me wearing personal protective equipment, I had a huge smile behind the face mask. Exploring the collections and going through dozens of dusty cabinets full of skeletons of </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Porites sp</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> never felt so good. It really felt like the months of working on my research from my computer was now finally coming to life!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A substantial part of my research involves gathering data of massive corals from turbid water environments in the Coral Triangle across different museum collections. I like to call this part of my research ‘data scavenging’ because it involves finding skeletons from different points in time to be able to build some timelines of coral growth rates and study how bioerosion intensity and community composition changed over the last two centuries. I spent all morning sorting through the drawers and found some very interesting specimens! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By the time I came across some nice samples from Singaporean waters, I was approaching lunchtime and could not help but see a sandwich-like skeleton in my hands. So I decided it was time for a break to have some lunch.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3361" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_porites-1.jpg" alt="" width="461" height="307" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_porites-1-200x133.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_porites-1-300x200.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_porites-1-400x266.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_porites-1.jpg 461w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 1: Side view of a skeleton of massive <em>Porites</em> with an apparent layered structure.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After a quick lunch, I started to sort and register all the prospective specimens that I could eventually take to the CT lab for scanning, once the CT lab resumes its activities. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">When I looked at the labels of some of the oldest specimens, I wondered how much of our world has changed since they had been collected in the field. Some of the oldest ones I found were still sealed air-dried skeletons dating back to 1890’s, a period when the oceans experienced just a fraction of the amount of man-made disturbances and pollution that coral reefs are subject to nowadays. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3360" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1.png" alt="" width="748" height="307" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1-200x82.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1-300x123.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1-400x164.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1-600x246.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leo_old-porites-1.png 748w" sizes="(max-width: 748px) 100vw, 748px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 2: Skeleton of massive <em>Porites</em> collected from Singaporean waters dating back to the late 1800s.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Time went by so quickly despite me being immersed in the collection from 10 am to 5 pm. I cannot wait to be back at the collection and see what else is out there waiting to tell their story about how coral reefs used to look like some 200 years ago.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Academic &#8216;Resilience&#8217;</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/leo-academic-resilience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 09:43:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3349</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London) In academia, we often do not associate the term ‘resilience’ with one’s individual ability to cope with challenging situations. Interestingly, if you ask an environmental scientist about the meaning of the term ‘resilience’, their reply will most likely be in the lines of ‘the ability of]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Leonardo Bertini (ESR at Natural History Museum London)</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In academia, we often do not associate the term ‘resilience’ with one’s individual ability to cope with challenging situations. Interestingly, if you ask an environmental scientist about the meaning of the term ‘resilience’, their reply will most likely be in the lines of ‘the ability of the living components of ecosystems to endure and adapt to a changing environment’. In today’s post, I approach resilience from a researcher’s perspective, sharing my personal experience following the easing of lockdown measures and resuming activities at the Natural History Museum in London.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pre-pandemic, we were all used to our daily commutes into our research institutes, sharing our lunch times with our colleagues and having the ease of access to all collections and labs. So when lockdown was announced, suddenly all of that academic freedom we were all so used to was quickly taken away. We all had to learn how to suddenly and quickly become ‘resilient’ to our ‘new conditions’, managing to continue our research with all these new restrictions in place!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Working from home became our new normal. From turning our dining tables in office tables to zoom calls with our collaborators and colleagues, all these new changes were part of us academics becoming more resilient. Personally, after many months working from home, I felt a sense of loss and was longing to return to the NHM. I missed looking up at the whale in Hintze Hall every morning, having lunch at the farmer’s market with colleagues and seeing my supervisors to discuss my research most days.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When it was announced that I was given clearance to visit the NHM collections, I was delighted! I was so happy to have a purposely driven commute to the NHM, after spending the last few months working from home. It is just one of those things that you start to realize how much you miss only after you have been deprived of that very same thing. I never thought I would be happy to get on the tube during rush hour to get to work!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For sure, the lockdown has affected everyone’s work to some extent, but I like to think of it in a positive way and, if anything, I would say we should see it as a time to reflect on our old habits and how much of the lifestyle we used to have was taken for granted. I would also like to see it as evidence as to how resilient we all have been during these difficult times, and that so many of us have been able to power on and find solutions to obstacles in order to continue our research, something we should all be very proud of!</span></p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
