<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>4D-REEF</title>
	<atom:link href="/4D-REEF/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/4D-REEF/</link>
	<description>Past, present, and future of  coral reefs in the Coral Triangle</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 12:36:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>NTA in Indonesia: A Tale of Two Cities (and ESRs): The Second Week</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/nta5-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 12:35:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Network Activities]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=4009</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Mariya Perepelytsya, based at Deltares (the Netherlands), and Kathrine Maxwell, based at Leibniz Center for Tropical Marine Research (Germany). All PhD's gathered for a network and training activity (NTA) in the field in Indonesia, for two weeks. After the first week in Makassar (read all about it in our previous blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Mariya Perepelytsya, based at Deltares (the Netherlands), and Kathrine Maxwell, based at Leibniz Center for Tropical Marine Research (Germany).</em></p>
<p>All PhD&#8217;s gathered for a network and training activity (NTA) in the field in Indonesia, for two weeks. After the first week in Makassar (read all about it in our <a href="/4D-REEF/nta5/">previous blog here</a>), we packed our bags and left our hotel to catch our flights to Denpasar in Bali where we stayed for another week of networking, workshops, and team-building activities (the Bali way).</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Week 2 in Bali</strong></span></h3>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Day 8</strong></span></h3>
<p><em>Mariya</em></p>
<p>The majority of us were flying to Denpasar at lunchtime. We were less lucky than Katt and Estra (who flew on another flight) and Bali welcomed us with a shower. However, even in the bad weather I was glued to the window of our bus on the way to the hotel! For someone who visited Bali for the first time, I was mesmerized by the rich architecture, temples, statues and blossoming flowers, not only on the trees around but in front of every place as daily offerings. We rounded the evening with a tasty group dinner and relaxed before the workday ahead of us.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4000" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="521" height="695" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-200x267.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-225x300.jpg 225w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-400x533.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-600x800.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-768x1024.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-800x1067.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-1200x1600.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-scaled.jpg 1440w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-1-Bali-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 100vw, 521px" /></p>
<p><em>Katt</em></p>
<p>Day 8: 0600H</p>
<p>Left the hotel very early to catch the morning flight to Denpasar. We were gifted with a very nice view of the Spermonde Archipelago. Bali welcomed us with fair weather. We had a short sweet break because of our travel from Makassar so we decided to walk along Sanur beach after grabbing lunch.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4004" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="437" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo9B.jpg 720w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 100vw, 583px" /></p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Day 9</strong></span></h3>
<p><em>Mariya</em></p>
<p>We were welcomed at the Coral Triangle Center, which is a non-profit foundation focusing on coral reef protection, education, supporting marine management and many other aspects in the field of marine conservation and sustainability. You can learn more here:  <a href="https://www.coraltrianglecenter.org/about-us/">https://www.coraltrianglecenter.org/about-us/</a>.</p>
<p>During the morning we got a chance to learn about the work done by the Center and experience first-hand various outreach activities aimed to inspire a wider audience in marine protection. These activities included team-played escape rooms, art exhibition “Harmony Island” by Mulyana, getting acquainted with the coral restoration projects across the Coral Triangle and the marine biodiversity database. What is more, you can take diving lessons and learn about the environmental best practices for diving and snorkeling. Impressively broad range of activities available at CTC for everyone!</p>
<p>During the afternoon, we engaged in discussions on collaboration initiatives between all the 4D-REEF ESR’s.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4001" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better.png" alt="" width="688" height="688" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-200x200.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-300x300.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-400x400.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-600x600.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-768x768.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-800x800.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-1024x1024.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-1200x1200.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better-1536x1536.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-2-better.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 688px) 100vw, 688px" /></p>
<p><em>Katt</em></p>
<p>0800H</p>
<p>We walked our way to the Coral Triangle Center (CTC) which is just several meters from the hotel. We learned about the CTC ‘s activities as an NGO focussed on marine protection and had team-building activities: the CTC escape rooms and marine-themed card game. We also had the afternoon full of discussions on collaborations between our projects.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4005" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="457" height="686" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-200x300.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-400x600.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-600x900.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-683x1024.jpg 683w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-768x1152.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-800x1200.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-1200x1800.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-scaled.jpg 1280w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo10-1365x2048.jpg 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Day 10</strong></span></h3>
<p><em>Mariya</em></p>
<p>It was a team-building day and nothing is better for that than having a trip together! Any words to describe it would be quite bleak in comparison to the natural beauty and cultural richness of the Ubud area. The only note for myself: if you can bike in the Netherlands with the phone in your hands (which is forbidden anyway), that doesn’t mean you should attempt filming everything around on the steep curvy roads, cause you may kiss the asphalt :D</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4002" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3.png" alt="" width="715" height="715" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-200x200.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-300x300.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-400x400.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-600x600.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-768x768.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-800x800.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-1024x1024.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-1200x1200.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3-1536x1536.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-3.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 715px) 100vw, 715px" /></p>
<p><em>Katt</em></p>
<p>0830H</p>
<p>We head down to Ubud district to continue with our team-building activities and cultural experience in Bali. I was really hesitant to go on biking around Ubud area at first, but after the experience, I was one of the people who enjoyed it the most. We cycled in different areas in Ubud seeing the traditional Bali houses, temples, and really good sceneries of rice fields. We went to Pura Puseh Desa Batuan, a Hindu temple, and to the Tegenungan Waterfall, a tourist spot.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4006" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="714" height="535" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-1536x1151.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo11-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 714px) 100vw, 714px" /></p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Day 11</strong></span></h3>
<p><em>Mariya</em></p>
<p>Ibu Rili Djohani &#8211; Executive Director and Founder of the Coral Triangle Center, welcomed us at the CTC and shared her professional development story and her work on “ Turning knowledge and science into the ground action”. From actions on local level via online CTC Academy and development of interactive learning activities (which we enjoyed as well on Day 9), inviting tourists and locals to think and care more about the oceans, to development of Indonesian National strategies for marine protected areas (MPAs) by 2030 and work on Ocean20 &#8211; Rili Djohani is a role model for young marine scientists and I was honoured to meet her.</p>
<p>Other speakers of the day were Ranny Yuneni, who told us about the population decline of endangered marine species and translation of the biodiversity protection efforts into policies; and representatives of organisations Pesisir Lestari and Blue ventures introduced us to their work on providing support for community-based octopus fisheries and management in Indonesia.</p>
<p>The day was concluded with a workshop by Dr. Arjun Chennu (Max-Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, and a supervisor in 4D-Reef) on data sharing &#8211; his experiences and role of open access data in facilitating knowledge exchange and collaborations.</p>
<p><em>Katt</em></p>
<p><em>0830h</em></p>
<p>We head back to the CTC to have another day of talks and discussions; this time about NGOs and how to make impact at various levels with science, from local to global policies.</p>
<p>We were welcomed by CTC Executive Director Rili Djohani and she kicked off the morning session with her talk on policy development and the role of NGOs in translating science into policy. Personally, I am really inspired by her work and advocacy on marine conservation and management. After the morning session about the work of NGOs in Indonesia, Dr. Arjun Chennu gave a workshop on data sharing—sharing his experiences and lessons learned about sharing data.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4007" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="603" height="909" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-199x300.jpg 199w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-200x302.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-400x603.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-600x905.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-679x1024.jpg 679w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-768x1158.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-800x1206.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-1019x1536.jpg 1019w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-1200x1810.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-scaled.jpg 1273w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo12-1358x2048.jpg 1358w" sizes="(max-width: 603px) 100vw, 603px" /></p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Day 12</strong></span></h3>
<p><em>Mariya</em></p>
<p>Early morning start to get to the Nusa Penida Marine Protected Area (MPA), to learn more in the field on coral reefs and mangroves.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the waves were too high to snorkel in the open waters with hope to see mantas in the Manta Bay, so we proceeded to Nusa Lembongan. There we visited the Mangrove forest with the boat tour around it and learned about the conservation initiatives to protect mangroves and their biodiversity in the area. After lunch, we snorkelled over the local reefs, explore the differences and similarities with the reefs near Makassar. And where we were lucky enough to see some dolphins and some of us a turtle. The abundance of colors was truly mesmerizing! The last stop of the day was the CTC community center on the island where we tagged reef stars (see previous blog, on the MARS project with reef stars) and placed them within the MPA. In the evening we concluded the 2 week NTA Indonesia with a team dinner.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4003" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5.png" alt="" width="770" height="770" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-200x200.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-300x300.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-400x400.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-600x600.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-768x768.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-800x800.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-1024x1024.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-1200x1200.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5-1536x1536.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Day-5.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 770px) 100vw, 770px" /></p>
<p><em>Katt</em></p>
<p><em>0723H</em></p>
<p>Day 5 in Bali. We took the boat and visited islands Nusa Penida and Nusa Lembongan. Here we visited a mangrove forest, learned more about coral reefs and coral restoration in the field, and participated in a coral tagging activity with Reef Stars (see also <a href="/4D-REEF/nta5/">our first blog</a> for more information about Reef Stars).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4008" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="782" height="587" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-1536x1153.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo13-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 782px) 100vw, 782px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Thank you, Bali. Thank you, Makassar. Thank you, Indonesia for welcoming us. We will definitely be back again. We were greeted by this rainbow during our second day in Bali.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-4010" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14.jpg" alt="" width="692" height="519" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo14.jpg 720w" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="post-content">
<p>*All photos made by 4D-Reef and ESRs.</p>
</div>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Mariya-Perepelytsya-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2745"><span class="esr-link">Mariya Perepelytsya</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Hydroinformatics and Water Management</p>
	<p>Deltares, Netherlands</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/KattMaxwell-N-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2737"><span class="esr-link">Kathrine Maxwell</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Geology</p>
	<p>Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research (ZMT), Germany</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What was the climate and ocean circulation of the Maritime Continent during a warmer period in the past?</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/climate-during-warmer-past/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 16:26:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modelling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[paper]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Xin Ren]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3991</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Xin Ren, based at University of Bristol. Figure 1 (at top of the page). PRISM4 Pliocene land-sea mask. The modern continental outline is indicated with black lines; blue and green shadings indicate ocean and land in the mPWP experiment. The red rectangle indicates the location of the Timor passage of the]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Xin Ren, based at University of Bristol.</em></p>
<p><em>Figure 1 (at top of the page). PRISM4 Pliocene land-sea mask. The modern continental outline is indicated with black lines; blue and green shadings indicate ocean and land in the mPWP experiment. The red rectangle indicates the location of the Timor passage of the Indonesian Throughflow (ITF). The red arrow denotes the position and direction of the ITF illustratively. The Sunda and Sahul shelves are illustrated in this figure via white labels. The continental outline is constructed from (Dowsett et al. 2016) and retrodicted with a set of procedures based on the paleogeographic maps of (Markwick 2007).</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Recently, I, Xin, explored the simulated climate of the Maritime Continent during the mid-Piacenzian period. The results will be published in my recent paper “The hydrological cycle and ocean circulation of the Maritime Continent in the mid-Pliocene: results from PlioMIP2” that is in preprint (<a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-1281">https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-1281</a>).</p>
<p>In this study, I used the Earth System Models to understand the hydrological cycle and ocean circulation of the Maritime Continent under this high CO<sub>2</sub> concentration induced warm period. The results provide us with a comprehensive and quantified sight into the changes in sea surface temperature, freshwater flux, salinity, wind stress and throughflow of the coral triangle, which can play an important role in coral reefs ecosystem.</p>
<p>Bullet points:</p>
<ol>
<li>In the mid-Piacenzian warm period, the climate of the Maritime Continent was warmer and wetter and the sea surface salinity in the surrounding ocean was lower compared with preindustrial.</li>
<li>In terms of the Indonesian Throughflow, 10 out of 15 models show an increased volume transport in the mid-Piacenzian warm period compared with preindustrial.</li>
</ol>
<p>The Maritime Continent (MC) forms the western boundary of the tropical Pacific Ocean. The Indonesian Throughflow (ITF) via the Maritime Continent is a key component of global ocean circulation. The ITF links the Pacific Ocean and the Indian Ocean by transporting warm and comparably fresh water from the Pacific Ocean into the Indian Ocean. Dramatic tectonic processes and sea level changes shaped this gateway that plays an important role in influencing local climate and that of other regions of the world. In the mid-Piacenzian warm period of the Pliocene (mPWP; 3.264 to 3.025 million years ago) atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were ~400 ppm, and the subaerial Sunda and Sahul shelves made the land-sea distribution of the MC different to today (Fig 1- top of the page). Topographic changes and elevated levels of CO2, combined with other forcings, are therefore expected to have driven a substantial climate signal in the MC region at this time.</p>
<p>By using the results from the Pliocene Model Intercomparison Project phase 2 (PlioMIP2), we study the mean climatic features of the MC in the mPWP and changes in ITF with respect to preindustrial. In this study we adopt the E280 simulation as a control experiment, which is forced with preindustrial conditions, and the Eoi400 simulation as a sensitivity experiment for mPWP conditions, which is forced with all mPWP boundary conditions; these are topography, ice sheets, soil, vegetation, lakes, land-sea mask and a concentration of 400 ppm of CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere. The boundary conditions for the PlioMIP2 experimental design can be downloaded from <a href="https://geology.er.usgs.gov/egpsc/prism/7.2_pliomip2_data.html">https://geology.er.usgs.gov/egpsc/prism/7.2_pliomip2_data.html</a>.</p>
<p>As shown in Fig 2, in line with the global climate, all the 17 PlioMIP2 models show higher SSTs in the mPWP MC, ranging from +0.43°C to +3.33°C, with a MMM warming by 1.88°C; 13 out of 17 models show fresh water flux increased in the MC, the anomaly ranging from +0.04 mm/day to +0.50 mm/day. In terms of atmospheric circulation, the easterlies over the western tropical Pacific Ocean show enhanced intensity in the MMM; there is anomalous eastward wind stress over the ocean near Western Australia. Seawater salinity affects the thermohaline circulation; 14 out of 16 models (model MRI-CGCM2.3 is absent here) show a lower SOS in the MC.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3994" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02.png" alt="" width="1825" height="1027" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-200x113.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-300x169.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-400x225.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-600x338.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-768x432.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-800x450.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-1024x576.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-1200x675.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02-1536x864.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f02.png 1825w" sizes="(max-width: 1825px) 100vw, 1825px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2. The MMM anomalies over the MC in the mPWP simulation relative to the preindustrial simulation for (a) sea surface temperature (SST), (b) precipitation minus evaporation (P-E), (c) zonal surface wind stress (TAUU) and (d) salinity at the ocean surface (SOS). In (a), circles mark the location of the SSTA proxies. Their colour represents the reconstructed SSTAs, the name of each site is indicated on the top of each circle. In (a) and (d), white shading indicates the grid boxes that are land for all the models, grid boxes outside the black lines are ocean grid boxes for all the models. In (b) and (c), hatches indicate land grid boxes in the mPWP experiment; the black lines indicate the continental outlines of the preindustrial experiment. In (b), filled circles denote proxy data in terms of wetter, or no-change condition. Details of each numbered site are shown in Table S2 in the supplement of the original paper. In (c), green shading indicates westward anomaly and purple shading indicates eastward anomaly. Stippled areas show significant multi-model differences according to a t-test at the 90% confidence level.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Temperature and density differences are factors that can contribute to changes in the ITF, which is an important process for regulating the climate of the MC. Therefore, we quantify and investigate the changes of oceanic flow through the MC in the mPWP. Even though the topography of the MC in the mPWP acts as a barrier for volume transport between the Pacific Ocean and the Indian Ocean compared to the preindustrial, 10 out of 15 models show the ITF intensity increasing by 5.6% to 43.8%. CESM2, IPSL-CM6A-LR, COSMOS, MIROCm4 and HadGEM3 show a decrease in intensity of the ITF, the amplitude of westward flow is here lowered by 3.4% to 39.4% (Fig 3b).</p>
<p>The spatial pattern of the vertical integrated zonal seawater volume transport anomaly is shown in Fig. 3a. There is a westward transport anomaly along the northeastern coast of the New Guinea, which favours the ocean mass transport of the ITF. For the oceanic transport through the gateway, the westward water transport via Timor passage has been strengthened over the north, but weakened over the south in the mPWP compared to the preindustrial. Moreover, the water mass is mainly transported through the ITF in the ocean above 1000 meters depth in both the preindustrial and the mPWP. The changes in the volume transport of ITF also mainly occur in the ocean above 1000 meters depth.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3995" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03.png" alt="" width="965" height="1090" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-200x226.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-266x300.png 266w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-400x452.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-600x678.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-768x867.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-800x904.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03-907x1024.png 907w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/f03.png 965w" sizes="(max-width: 965px) 100vw, 965px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3. (a) The MMM zonal seawater volume transport anomaly in the mPWP experiment relative to the preindustrial experiment. Blue shading indicates westward anomaly and brown shading indicates eastward anomaly. The red line is the transect to calculate the ocean volume transport intensity in (b). The hatches indicate land grid boxes in the mid-Pliocene experiment; the black lines indicate the continental outlines of the preindustrial experiment. (b) The integrated ocean volume transport intensity through the gateway. Negative values indicate westward transport. Stippled areas show significant multi-model differences according to a t-test at the 90% confidence level.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>References</em>:<br />
Dowsett, H., and Coauthors, 2016: The PRISM4 (mid-Piacenzian) paleoenvironmental reconstruction. Clim. Past, 12, 1519–1538, <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-12-1519-2016">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-12-1519-2016</a>.<br />
Markwick, P. J., 2007: The palaeogeographic and palaeoclimatic significance of climate proxies for data-model comparisons. Geol. Soc. Spec. Publ., 251–312, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/tms002.13">https://doi.org/10.1144/tms002.13</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin-Ren-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-1-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2747"><span class="esr-link">Xin Ren</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Quaternary Geology</p>
	<p>University of Bristol, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Max at the 6th International Sclerochronology Conference</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/isc/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 14:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fursman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3978</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Max Fursman, based at Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany   The scientific community is a vibrant tapestry of intellect, curiosity, and collaboration that spans across borders and unites researchers from all corners of the world. Among the myriad of scientific events that showcase this international camaraderie is the International Sclerochronology Conference. The]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Max Fursman, based at Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The scientific community is a vibrant tapestry of intellect, curiosity, and collaboration that spans across borders and unites researchers from all corners of the world. Among the myriad of scientific events that showcase this international camaraderie is the International Sclerochronology Conference.<br />
The 6<sup>th</sup> ISC took place in Tokyo, Japan in May this year, as scientists from all over the globe either travelled or attended virtually to discuss all things sclerchronological (study of physical and chemical variations in the accretionary hard tissues of organisms).</p>
<p>I was representing 4D-Reef and Tridacna.</p>
<p>Usually the conference is held every 3 years but thanks to the pandemic the 6<sup>th</sup> sessions, which was due to take place in May 2022, was postponed by a year and a student run online conference was run instead.</p>
<p>After 19 hours and forty minutes of travel, or in other terms: 5 imodium-laced microwave-heated meals; 4 movies I had missed in cinemas; 3 hours of napping on a bench in Taipei airport cradling my laptop like a cabbage patch doll, I touched down in the Land of the Rising Sun.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3984" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1.png" alt="" width="624" height="311" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-200x100.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-300x150.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-400x199.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-600x299.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-768x383.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture1.png 780w" sizes="(max-width: 624px) 100vw, 624px" /></p>
<p>I ate about a year’s worth of ramen in the few days before the conference…</p>
<p>The conference took place at the Hongo campus of the University of Tokyo, where in 1925 Prof. Hidesaburō Ueno died while lecturing. His loyal Akita dog Hachikō, who had learnt to wait for his owner to return at Shinuya station every day, continued to go and wait every day after his owner failed to return for nine years until he himself died… (Pass me the tissues)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3985" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2.png" alt="" width="615" height="491" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-177x142.png 177w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-200x160.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-300x240.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-400x320.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-600x479.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-768x614.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-800x639.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture2.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 615px) 100vw, 615px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left: The banner proudly guiding us to the Yayoi Auditorium</em><br />
<em>Right – Top: Hongo Campus, University of Tokyo</em><br />
<em>Right – Bottom: the heartbreaking statue of Prof. Ueno and Hachikō</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Hats off to the organising committee, let by Dr. Kotaro Shirai, as they did a truly superb job right from the get go.</p>
<p>Sunday evening we were welcomed to the meeting with an ice-breaker event where they had really pulled out all the stops. We were served a buffet of Japanese food, with opportunities to eat more mochi than the human body really should, sample Japanese wines and beers and were entertained by final year music students in what turned out to be a very entertaining, though somewhat cramped, evening that settled everyone comfortably in for the week.</p>
<p>The conference itself was a stupendous and ran smooth as silk.<br />
The talks were a mixture of in person talks with some speakers joining via zoom from other countries, and covered topics from in depth sclerochemical analysis in fossil samples, to anthropology studies on shell remains in ancient middens.<br />
Some of the keynote talks on biomineralisation, sclera-proxy development and evolutionary paleobiology were especially interesting. One in particular, delivered by Prof. Burchell from Memorial University’s Department of Archaeology, was thought provoking and resonated with a lot of those assembled. Entitled “Imagining a Radical Future for Archaeology and Sclerochronology”, the talk focused on the use of Indigenous and native groups to regions that are used for research or sample collection, and how their input into the studies should be taken on board and the culture and traditions respected and included as part of our work. It left a lot to think about and prompted some healthy discussion during the next break.</p>
<p>Speaking of, the coffee breaks were held in the poster area and yet again Kotaro et al came through with a variety of Japanese cakes and snacks available to sample and gorge on!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3986" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3.png" alt="" width="693" height="554" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-177x142.png 177w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-200x160.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-300x240.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-400x320.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-600x479.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-768x614.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-800x639.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture3.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 693px) 100vw, 693px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left – top: The crowded ice-breaker event, with food galore and drinks flowing! </em><br />
<em>Left – bottom: the final day group photo!</em><br />
<em>Right – top: One very handsome sclerochronologist presenting his work on Tridacna  sclerochemistry, representing 4D-Reef</em><br />
<em>Right – bottom: musicians playing for us during the ice-breaker</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I was excited to present on my research, and spoke on a topic I had presented at ICRS last July, a long-term study into induced-seasonality in a tridacna sample. Since ICRS we have been able to expand our work into a greater depth and understanding and the chance to discuss it at a niche and specific conference where others would have intimate knowledge on the topic was a great opportunity. Myself and several others who study tridacna gathered afterwards to discuss our own work in depth and have since kept in contact and formed a slack group to trade ideas and promote further discourse on our sclerochemical endevours. While the virtual student ISC last September was interesting and engaging, the in person nature of a conference is something that cannot be replicated. These exchanges with people engaged in similar veins of work, and even those engaged in more general sclera-studies, have offered a chance to open up new avenues for collaboration and expanded my understanding of sclerochronology from various perspectives. The global nature of the conference facilitated interactions with scholars from different countries, fostering an enriching environment of cultural diversity and intellectual exchange.</p>
<p>Another treat organised by Kotaro et al was the conference dinner, which was a stupendous affair.</p>
<p>Held high up in Royal Park Hotel Tokyo we were treated to a buffet banquet overlooking Tokyo at night. Traditional foods, as well as Sake and beer, seemed to be in endless supply, with a tempura cooking display churning out fresh delicious snacks all evening.<br />
The evening ended with a wonderful recital of traditional music on koto, the national instrument of Japan. It was mesmerizing to watch the skill and deft movements needed to pluck and tune this instrument and to charm such sweet melodies out.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3987" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4.png" alt="" width="627" height="501" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-177x142.png 177w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-200x160.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-300x240.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-400x320.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-600x479.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-768x614.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-800x639.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture4.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left &#8211; top: The musicians playing the traditional koto for us in a beautiful demonstration.<br />
</em><em>Left – bottom: a group of scientists standing round enjoying the food and drinks, one in particular wearing a VERY fetching batik shirt…<br />
</em><em>Right – top: the group photo following the meal<br />
</em><em>Right – bottom: the view from the dining room overlooking Tokyo at night</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Beyond the confines of the conference halls, Tokyo unfolded as a captivating tapestry of cultural splendor. Each moment spent in the city was a sensory delight, offering an array of experiences that seamlessly blended ancient traditions with modern marvels. Any street could have simultaneously modern skyscrapers and stores, yet nestled within it is an untouched temple where the noise and bustle of the city seems to melt away. I found myself enthralled by the harmonious coexistence of serenity and dynamism that defined Tokyo.<br />
We took our time to immerse ourselves in this new place, visiting temples, tourist attractions and trying our hand at karaoke!<br />
One absolute highlight was a trip we took out to the coastal town of Enoshima, and the island just off the coast. Far from there, standing on the skyline, was the snow-capped peak of Mt. Fuji, piercing the sky with its grandeur. A slight fog added a mystic, ethereal haze to the scene, and the sheer beauty of the mountain seared itself into my mind.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3988" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5.png" alt="" width="581" height="464" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-177x142.png 177w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-200x160.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-300x240.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-400x320.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-600x479.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-768x614.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-800x639.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture5.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left –top: Me in front of Sensō-ji temple, Tokyo<br />
</em><em>Left – bottom: Iris finding Tridacna for sale at the beach. Sadly CITES might have taken issue to putting it in our carry-on…<br />
</em><em>Middle – top: Up in the hills at Kiyomizu-dera temple, Kyoto<br />
</em><em>Middle – middle: Inside the Torii tunnel on the mountain of Fushimi Inari-Taisha shrine<br />
</em><em>Middle – bottom: Mt. Fuji through the clouds, across the bay from Enoshima Island<br />
</em><em>Right – top: Meeting a celebrity at the Studio Ghibli shop (ignore the socks and shorts)<br />
</em><em>Right – bottom – quietly enjoying costume karaoke with my fellow conference attendees</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>What truly was a treat though, was Tokyo&#8217;s culinary scene. It proved to be a delight for the senses and I indulged in what can only be described as a gastronomic adventure in my spare time. Ramen, sushi, tempura, gyoza, I tried anything and everything I could. Some of it was unusual, such as the konjac, or devil’s tongue potato, which proved to have a tasty but fat/gelatin-like consistency when stewed. But everything was delicious and there is not one item I wouldn’t order again in a heartbeat.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3989" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture6.png" alt="" width="368" height="520" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture6-200x283.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture6-212x300.png 212w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture6-400x565.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture6.png 510w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>A sampling of the food consumed on this trip</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Overall, the journey from Frankfurt to Tokyo for the 6th International Sclerochronology Conference was an extraordinary experience that blended scientific exploration with cultural immersion. The conference itself proved to be a hub of knowledge, where ideas flowed freely, collaborations flourished, and new contacts made.<br />
Beyond the academic sphere, Tokyo&#8217;s vibrant culture, awe-inspiring landmarks, and culinary wonders created a tapestry of experiences that left an indelible mark on my journey.</p>
<p>From presenting my research findings to engaging in stimulating discussions with experts in the field, I felt the conference fostered personal and professional growth. Tokyo, with its harmonious blend of tradition and innovation, captivated my senses, offering a glimpse into the rich cultural heritage of Japan, and I am grateful for the opportunities to learn, connect, and explore.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3990" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture7.jpg" alt="" width="276" height="207" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture7-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture7-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture7-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Picture7.jpg 532w" sizes="(max-width: 276px) 100vw, 276px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Sunset behind the main entrance Torii (sacred arch at shrine/temple entrances) at Fushimi Inari-Taisha shrine</em></p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Max-Fursman-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2743"><span class="esr-link">Max Fursman</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy and Biodiversity</p>
	<p>Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Digitizing the Spermonde coral reefs: a paradise of corals, turf- and coralline algae</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/digitizing-the-spermonde-coral-reefs-a-paradise-of-corals-turf-and-coralline-algae/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 15:20:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[benthos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daniel Schürholz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dino Angelo Ramos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Estradivari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UNHAS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3971</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Daniel Christoph Schürholz, Dino Ramos and Estradivari, based at respectively the Max-Planck-Institute for Marine Microbiology, University of Granada and Leibniz-zentrum fur Tropical Marine Research.   Digitizing the Spermonde coral reefs: a paradise of corals, turf and algae Finally! During August of last year (2022), we went to our promised field sites]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Daniel Christoph Schürholz, Dino Ramos and Estradivari, based at respectively the Max-Planck-Institute for Marine Microbiology, University of Granada and Leibniz-zentrum fur Tropical Marine Research.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Digitizing the Spermonde coral reefs: a paradise of corals, turf and algae</strong></p>
<p>Finally! During August of last year (2022), we went to our promised field sites in the beautiful sandy islands of the Spermonde Archipelago, just in front of the bustling city of Makassar &#8211; South Sulawesi &#8211; Indonesia. This archipelago is located in the heart of the marine biodiversity hotspot known as the Coral Triangle, a dream destination for marine researchers. Almost three years we waited to go, and just after the pandemic regulations and global crises relaxed a tiny bit, we packed our (many) bags and went to the field. Each one of us early stage researchers (ESRs) had planned their sampling strategies and locations carefully, considering our research goals, but also accounting for possible collaborations within the team and/or with our amazing partners from the local Hasanuddin University (UNHAS) in Makassar. This specific story is about the collaboration of three 4D-REEF ESRs: Estra, Dino and Daniel, with three outstanding Indonesian students from UNHAS: Phita, Gunawan and Agung, who all flew from the warm Indonesian weather to the frosty German winter.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3959" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-800x533.jpeg" alt="" width="800" height="533" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-200x133.jpeg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-300x200.jpeg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-400x267.jpeg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-600x400.jpeg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-768x512.jpeg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-800x533.jpeg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/01_team.jpeg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>The digitizers working hard at the Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research ZMT (from left to right): Estra, Gunawan, Agung, Dino, Phita, Daniel.</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Something in common: reef benthos</strong></p>
<p>To collaborate within our small team we had to identify what binds our three research projects together. And luckily, the link was easy to find, since in all our cases we are interested in the coral reef benthos (a.k.a., the habitat on the seafloor).</p>
<p>In Estra’s project, for example, she is looking at the ecological implications of shifts from hard corals to turf algae (assemblages of many diminutive species of algae) in turbid reefs. Turf algae and corals live in balance unless the ecosystem is disturbed (usually by man-made pressures), in which case the loss of coral could mean an overexpansion of turf algae. Estra, along with four students from UNHAS, studies the reef&#8217;s turf algae mats and how they change over time, as well as their role in the ecosystem (i.e., trapping sediments and detritus &#8211; Gunawan; providing nutritious food for herbivorous fish &#8211; Munawarrah; competing of space with hard corals and other biotas &#8211; Agung) and their interactions with other organisms, such as corals and fish (Puspita).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3960" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-800x680.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="680" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-200x170.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-300x255.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-400x340.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-600x510.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-768x653.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-800x680.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-1024x870.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-1200x1020.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-1536x1305.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/02_turf-algae-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>Turf algae mats covered dead corals on Samalona Island. In reefs near Makassar City (e.g., Lae Lae, Samalona), where sedimentation and river run-off were significant, turf algae mats can cover more than 50% of the bottom substrate and trap a large amount of sediment and detritus. Offshore reefs exhibit fewer turf algae assemblages and sediments/detritus trapped within turf algae (e.g., Kapoposang, Karang Kassi).</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Dino’s research focuses on the crustose coralline algae (CCA), a type of red algae with calcified thalli (term referring to algal bodies). They are a key player in the ecosystem, as they are considered to literally build the reef framework together with stony corals (juvenile corals also seem to prefer them when selecting a place to settle). Dino is looking into the diversity of these often overlooked organisms and how their communities shift with varying conditions in the reef, particularly turbidity, in the Spermonde Archipelago.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3961" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-800x300.png" alt="" width="800" height="300" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-200x75.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-300x113.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-400x150.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-600x225.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-768x288.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-800x300.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-1024x384.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-1200x450.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA-1536x576.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/04_CCA.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>While not immediately noticeable in most coral reefs, you only need to look in the spaces among the corals to find the ubiquitous CCA. Like the more colorful corals, they can take various morphologies such as the branching form seen in the right image in between the Acropora. Currently twenty species of CCA have been described in the Spermonde Archipelago based on morpho-anatomical characters. This is likely an underestimation based on the abundance of cryptic species detected in recent studies of CCA using DNA. With a lack of basic taxonomic knowledge, even less is known about each of these species’ ecological functions!</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Daniel’s project targets the creation of maps of the coral reefs, describing the whole benthic ecosystem by applying advanced underwater imaging techniques and artificial intelligence (AI) pipelines. Understanding the spatial distribution of organisms on the maps can help to identify their specific life strategies and adaptability in the case of future changes to their environments.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3962" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-1024x764.png" alt="" width="1024" height="764" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-200x149.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-300x224.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-400x299.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-600x448.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-768x573.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-800x597.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-1024x764.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps-1200x896.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/05_habitat_maps.png 1341w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><i>Examples of habitat maps created from data acquired using the HyperDiver camera system in Curacaoan coral reefs in the Caribbean. Habitat maps such as these help scientists elucidate the spatial distributions of organisms and substrate types in their ecosystems. If created over a temporal period they also help understand interactions between the organisms and their environment. Overall, maps are a great monitoring tool that can influence important conservation and ecological management decisions.</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>All of our projects require the base knowledge that comes from answering 2 questions: what class of organisms and substrates can be found in the reefs of Spermonde? And how much/many of each class can be found in the reefs?</p>
<p>To answer these questions we organized secondments, where we could exchange our expertise to make the best out of the data we collected in the field work. Thus, we organized a big 6 week workshop, and with help of the Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research (ZMT), the Max-Planck-Institute for Marine Microbiology (MPIMM), the University of Granada (UGR), and the 4D-REEF central organization board in Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden we invited the three Indonesian students to Bremen, Germany. The workshop took place from the 9th of January until the 17th of February 2023.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>So many pictures, so little time!</strong></p>
<p>The data and tools each of us collected on our field trip were very similar, only with differing strategies. We all collected top-down images of the seafloor and wanted to annotate (label) all the organisms we found in them. This is not as trivial as it may sound though. Between Estra and Dino and their team, they collected almost 5000 pictures! Daniel also collected over 60000 images (it’s not a competition, but who’s counting?). No life of ours could be spent annotating all 65000 images. At this point we decided that some automation, inspired by the current AI boom, was needed. But even the smartest of computers needs some manual help from us primitive humans, to learn what exactly to detect in the images.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Automatic point annotations</strong></p>
<p>For the first set of images (~5000) we wanted to annotate a random selection of 50 points (pixels) with a meaningful label. Estra and her students carefully detailed a set of 73 labels (a labelset) describing all organisms and substrates to be found on the coral reef floor. Later we reduced the labelset to 37 labels, for better performance when automating the process. Then, armed with this labelset, the “Coral Point Count with excel extension (CPCe)” software and full commitment, they annotated 821 images.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3963" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/06_annotating-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>Although image annotation is done individually, this workshop fostered team discussions and knowledge sharing, leading to a better image annotation process and benthic identification.</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This set of human-annotated images was then the input to a machine learning (ML) web service called <a href="https://coralnet.ucsd.edu/">CoralNet (</a><a href="https://coralnet.ucsd.edu/">link)</a>. In this great software offered publicly by the University of California in San Diego (UCSD), a set of pre-annotated images is uploaded, used for training a complex neural network, which in turn is used to predict the annotations on new uploaded images, which do not contain any previous annotations. As part of the ESRs’ secondments we all gathered in Bremen Germany, and went over a 3 week workshop, to learn how to set up the CoralNet project and to establish the benefits of such technologies.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3964" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-800x800.png" alt="" width="456" height="456" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-200x200.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-300x300.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-400x400.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-600x600.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-768x768.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-800x800.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-1024x1024.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-1200x1200.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary-1536x1536.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/07_point_annotations_summary.png 3000w" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" /></p>
<p><i>The manual Coral Point Count annotations done by Estra and her students amounted to 41050 points over 37 benthic classes in 821 images! These points were used to train the CoralNet machine learning algorithm.</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>After training the networks, we tried the first predictions on new images. Because of the complexity of such an ecosystem, the different lighting conditions and possible human error in the annotations, the accuracy of the network was good but not great (57% accuracy). Nonetheless, the CoralNet platform allows to then manually confirm the annotations, by suggesting possible candidates for each new point in each new image. This can reduce the time of annotating significantly (still to be quantified). For comparison, it took three students almost three months to annotate 821 images, whereas CoralNet finished over 4000 images in a couple of hours. There are other parameters that can as well be tweaked to make the predictions more confident. Overall the outcome of the process was positive and we will continue to use its outputs for our study results.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3965" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-800x281.png" alt="" width="800" height="281" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-200x70.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-300x106.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-400x141.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-600x211.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-768x270.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-800x281.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-1024x360.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC-1200x422.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/08_CPC.png 1436w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>Image with CPCe annotations (left) and a view of CoralNet annotation suggestions with a confidence percentage provided by the AI (right).</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Manual polygon annotations</strong></p>
<p>The other big batch of images (~60k) was captured using the HyperDiver (<a href="/4D-REEF/coral-reef-habitat-mapping-in-corona-times/">see Daniel&#8217;s blog (link)</a> ) by a team of great divers (Dino, Agung, Agus, Dedi, Supardi, Asriadi and Masdar) and one lone snorkeler (Daniel). In contrast to our previous set of images, these were stitched together to create a larger view of the seafloor (an orthomosaic), by a process called photogrammetry. The advantage of these larger scenes is that it is easy to georeference the data, and to create a better spatial description of the seafloor habitat and organism communities. In total we collected 13 of these large plots across 5 islands.</p>
<p>To manually annotate every organism in these large images would be a cumbersome effort. Thus, we decided to annotate a smaller subset of every organism/substrate type that we found, in order to train machine learning networks to automatically annotate the rest of the area for us. We planned the manual annotation part of the process to take place during the last three weeks of the secondment project.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3966" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-800x307.png" alt="" width="800" height="307" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-200x77.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-300x115.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-400x154.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-600x230.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-768x295.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-800x307.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-1024x393.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-1200x461.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab-1536x590.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/09_taglab.png 3032w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>TagLab annotation tool with coral-colony-annotations highlighted. We aimed at annotating as far down the taxonomic tree as possible. In the case of coral, we were able to use genus-level labels, given the high resolution of the orthomosaics and the high level of expertise from our annotators.</i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>By using <a href="http://taglab.isti.cnr.it/">TagLab (link)</a>, a great tool developed by the Visual Computing Laboratory in Italy, we again started annotating many organisms and substrate types in the images, with the only difference being that now we annotated polygons instead of single points. This process is usually tedious and time consuming when using a non-specialized tool, such as a GIS platform, but with the tools that TagLab offers, the process was significantly improved. After a quick introduction to the tools by Daniel, and in only three weeks, the amazing students Phita, Gunawan and Agung, drew and annotated almost 1600 polygons across 3 of the large plots! The labelset used in these annotations has great detail, and covers 36 coral genera, many soft coral genera, sponges, anemones, cyanobacterial mats, turf algae, amongst many other organisms and substrate types. In a further research study these annotations will be used to train an advanced machine learning algorithm to detect individual organisms as well as their surrounding environments with great accuracy. The fully annotated maps created by the AI will then be used to elucidate spatial characteristics of the coral reefs and hopefully set a baseline for future studies.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3967" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-800x800.png" alt="" width="455" height="455" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-200x200.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-300x300.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-400x400.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-600x600.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-768x768.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-800x800.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-1024x1024.png 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-1200x1200.png 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary-1536x1536.png 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/10_polygons_annotations_summary.png 3000w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" /></p>
<p><i>The result of the orthomosaic annotation was great for only 3 weeks of intense annotations. We created 1596 polygons down to genus level for corals, soft corals and macroalgae, as well as other biota and substrate types.</i></p>
<p><b><br />
</b><strong>Closing thoughts</strong></p>
<p>We had a great time during the secondment and annotation workshop, which was the conclusion to getting to know each other during the field trip and planning and executing a collaboration with a transdisciplinary and multi-cultural team. We produced knowledge that will help each of us through our career paths and learned to collaborate and communicate with local partners, a much needed skill if we want to make science accessible and visible to researchers worldwide.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3968" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-800x541.jpeg" alt="" width="800" height="541" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-200x135.jpeg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-300x203.jpeg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-400x271.jpeg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-600x406.jpeg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-768x520.jpeg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-800x541.jpeg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-1024x693.jpeg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1-1200x812.jpeg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/11_dinner-1.jpeg 1312w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><i>Having a delicious Peruvian meal (at the “Pachamama” restaurant in Bremen) with the team and Katherine Maxwell, another 4D-Reef member based in Bremen, was a great way to end the secondment.</i></p>
<p>Finally, we, the ESRs and UNHAS students, would like to thank everybody who made this small collaborative effort possible, starting by our institutes, the Naturalis team, our fellow ESRs, our supervisors, but specially to the amazing team in Indonesia, who welcomed us from the beginning and created such a nice atmosphere to work in, besides giving valuable input/guidance/sweat-and-hard-work for our projects; Terima kasih!</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Estradivari-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2729"><span class="esr-link">Estradivari</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Environment and Resource Management</p>
	<p>Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research (ZMT), Germany</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Daniel-Christoph-Schurholz-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-1-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2726"><span class="esr-link">Daniel Christoph Schürholz</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Computer Science</p>
	<p>Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, Germany</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Dino-Angelo-Ramos-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2739"><span class="esr-link">Dino Angelo Ramos</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy, Biodiversity and Evolution</p>
	<p>University of Granada, Spain</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>NTA5 in Indonesia: A Tale of Two Cities (and ESRs) &#8211; part 1</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/nta5/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 15:35:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Network Activities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kathrine Maxwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mariya Perepelytsya]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NTA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Mariya Perepelytsya, based at Deltares (the Netherlands), and Kathrine Maxwell, based at Leibniz Center for Tropical Marine Research (Germany).   Last 17 to 29 October 2022, the 4D-REEF Team went to Indonesia for the fifth Networking and Training Activity (NTA) after almost 2.5 years of waiting. It was two weeks of,]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESRs Mariya Perepelytsya, based at Deltares (the Netherlands), and Kathrine Maxwell, based at Leibniz Center for Tropical Marine Research (Germany).</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Last 17 to 29 October 2022, the 4D-REEF Team went to Indonesia for the fifth Networking and Training Activity (NTA) after almost 2.5 years of waiting. It was two weeks of, well, networking and training activities, with the ESRs and our Indonesian colleagues. We spent our first week in Makassar in South Sulawesi and our second week in Denpasar in Bali, visiting the island communities, snorkeling on the reefs, learning from local experts, and seeing the marine conservation efforts in the region along with enjoying the Indonesian culture and, most especially, good food. It was generally a memorable experience for the ESRs as we have gotten closer and learned useful information, especially now that the program comes to its fruition. As we were also joined by our Indonesian colleagues, some of us even got closer to our Indonesian friends (and some had the chance to meet new ones). We thought of sharing with you a glimpse of some of the memorable experiences we had during the NTA – the activities, the reefs, and the tasty food and good company.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Week 1 in Makassar</strong></span></h3>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-0 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Sunday &#8211; Day 0</strong></span></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><b>Mariya</b></span></p>
<p>After 38 hours on the go I was finally rewarded with a luxury of a hot shower and a comfortable bed. Not a lot of sleep, as in the morning I had to rush for a tasty breakfast and enjoying the view of the sea from my window. After meeting most of the 4D-REEF team and having coffee for some functioning, I joined a part of the team in discovering our surroundings. We visited the Fort of Rotterdam, all that effort and long way, and yet I am back to Rotterdam again!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In the evening most of us arrived in Makassar, so it was time for a group dinner, live music and trying the first Indonesian cuisine dishes.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-1 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3932" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1A-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Sunset view from Belhotel on Lae-Lae.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-2 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-3 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><b>Katt</b></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Day 0: 0100H</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Arrived in Makassar around Sunday midnight. Was tired from the &gt;one day travel from Bremen to Makassar but was welcomed by the nice view and good food in Indonesia.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3921" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-1B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>View of Makassar from the Hotel </em></p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-4 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Monday &#8211; Day 1</span><br />
</strong></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><b>Mariya</b></span></p>
<p>Jetlag wasn’t kind to me &#8211; after no night&#8217;s sleep, I joined Katt and others in the hotel’s conference room. We finally met our colleagues from the University of Hasanuddin in person and got to know each other better through the ice-breaker activities. And let’s not forget the 4D-REEF distinguished bags for everyone ;)</p>
<p>On a serious note, we learned a lot about the local fisheries and their governance and the difficulties the fishermen face in their day-to-day life.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-5 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3933" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2A-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>The 4D-REEF tote bag!</em></p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-6 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-7 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 1: 0900H</p>
<p>Start of the NTA program in Swiss-Belhotel in Makassar where we had a whole day of talks about coastal livelihood and fisheries in Indonesia. I was introduced to the fishing culture and social organization in Indonesia. The talks made me think how complex the fishing industry in Indonesia is and how it is tied to social relationships between various agents and institutions.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em> </em><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3922" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-800x677.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="677" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-200x169.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-300x254.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-400x339.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-600x508.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-768x650.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-800x677.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-1024x867.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-1200x1016.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-1536x1300.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-2B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Whole day of talks on marine management and conservation, and reef restoration efforts in Indonesia. Prof. Adi Maulana (vice-rector of UNHAS University) and Dr. Willem Renema (top photo) started off the program with some welcome remarks. A series of talks followed with Dr. Sebastian Ferse (bottom left photo) giving an overview of the Spermonde archipelago social-ecological system and Dr. Dedi Adhuri (bottom right photo) talking about the fishing culture in eastern Indonesia.</em></p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-8 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Tuesday &#8211; Day 2</span><br />
</strong></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya </strong></span></p>
<p>We were welcomed by Prof. Jamaluddin Jompa at UNHAS, and our programme followed with a set of seminars on marine management and conservation. I was shocked and inspired at the same time by the talk of Tries Razak, PhD, on reef restoration practices. Inspired by successful ones and shocked by the destructive impacts of poorly-designed ones. All of our actions have consequences, so quality above quantity &#8211; we should remember that in our work as well.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-9 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3934" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-800x605.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="605" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-200x151.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-300x227.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-400x302.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-600x454.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-768x581.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-800x605.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-1024x774.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-1200x907.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-1536x1161.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3A_-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>4D-REEF at UNHAS (top photo). Dr. Tries Razak giving a talk on coral reef conservation practices&#8212;the unsuccessful shown on the bottom left photo and the successful practices shown on the bottom right photo.</em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-10 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-11 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 2: 0900H</p>
<p>We went to Universitas Hasanuddin (UNHAS) campus for another day of talks this time on marine management and conservation as well as reef restoration efforts in Indonesia. We were welcomed by UNHAS Rector Prof. Jamaluddin Jompa and this was followed by a series of talks about the latest developments in marine research and management in Indonesia. In particular, I find the success story of the MARS project really inspiring.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3923" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-800x634.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="634" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-200x159.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-300x238.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-400x317.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-600x476.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-768x609.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-800x634.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-1024x812.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-1200x951.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-1536x1218.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-3B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Day of talks in UNHAS. We were warmly welcomed by UNHAS Rector, Prof. Jamaluddin Jompa (left photo). Dr. Udhi Eko Hernawan, director of the Research Center for Oceanography of the National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN) (right photo) kicked off the day’s session with his talk on science for coastal management in Indonesia.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-12 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Wednesday &#8211; Day 3</span><br />
</strong></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya </strong></span></p>
<p>Dream day &#8211; field day!</p>
<p>We started with Barrang Lompo and visited the UNHAS field station and had a walk around the island to learn about the livelihood of the island. Colourful houses, many built with sturdy massive corals, kids, riding the “daycare” bike-cart with music and fishermen, drying their catch in the hot midday sun. Some of them dried trepang &#8211;  sea cucumbers &#8211; the marine animal of great value, captured from the sea bottom (a dangerous process of capture for fishermen) and sold to China. The people of Makassar traded sea cucumbers with Indigineous Australians and China since the 18th century en-masse. Sadly, because of the expensive price of sea-cucumbers, none of the local fishermen we met have ever tried even a tiny piece of the animal &#8211; all of the capture is sold overseas.</p>
<p>On the next islands we visited &#8211;  Pulau Bonetambung and Pulao Kudingareng Lompo, we learned about the local community initiative to set up an aquaculture facility and a primary school for kids to get the basic education. Life on those further islands from Makassar city is also complicated by the shortages of fresh water, and we witnessed how locals are dealing with this issue in their households.</p>
<p>And I also learned a lot from the local people &#8211; big smiles, music and happiness &#8211; despite all of the hardships they have daily, they are genuinely happy, with everything the day brings to them &#8211; something we need to remind ourselves more often about!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-13 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3935" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-800x911.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="911" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-200x228.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-263x300.jpg 263w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-400x456.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-600x683.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-768x875.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-800x911.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-899x1024.jpg 899w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-1200x1367.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-1349x1536.jpg 1349w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-scaled.jpg 1686w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4a_-1798x2048.jpg 1798w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Drying of trepang – sea cucumbers (top photos, photos by Xin Ren). Pulau Bonetambung: fishing boats (bottom left) and scale of decomposition time, years,  of different materials of litter (bottom right)</em></p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-14 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-15 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 3: 0700H</p>
<p>Field day! Yay! We visited select islands of the Spermonde archipelago—Barrang Lompo, Pulau Bonetambung, and Pulau Kudingarenglompo—to have a look at the coastal communities and their livelihoods on the islands. What strikes me the most is that the ones we visited are really low-lying islands and are densely populated. Also they use corals as foundations of their houses and coastal walls. We had dinner at Konro Karebosi with almost everyone. One of the best restaurants one must visit when coming to Makassar!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3924" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-4B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>View of low-lying Bonetambung Island.</em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-16 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Thursday &#8211; Day 4</span></strong></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya</strong></span></p>
<p>Guided by Lily Damayanti and Cudo Prasetya, we witnessed HOPE of MARS coral restoration project efforts. 14m-long letters are built from hundreds of  reef stars &#8211; 3D stable steel structures coated in resin and sand for creating a surface for coral attachment. Overall,coral fragments from 42 species and collected sustainably (e.g. from breakage after storms) from nearby reefs with similar environmental conditions to facilitate coral survivability and are attached to reef stars.</p>
<p>Also, I snorkelled for the first time ever! An exciting day, with bumps of leaking snorkel tubes :D But enjoying the day with our amazing boat crew and being rewarded by them with tasty donuts &#8211; all the efforts were worth it!</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-17 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3936" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-800x1067.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="1067" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-200x267.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-225x300.jpg 225w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-400x533.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-600x800.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-768x1024.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-800x1067.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5A.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><em>4D-REEF group photo in Pulau Badi.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="size-fusion-800 wp-image-3930 alignnone aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-800x381.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="381" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-200x95.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-300x143.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-400x191.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-600x286.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-768x366.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-800x381.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-1024x488.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-1200x572.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1-1536x732.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Bontosua-HOPE-1.jpg 1833w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><em>You can see HOPE from Google Earth (Google Earth).</em></p>
<p><div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-18 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-19 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 4: 0700H</p>
<p>Field day: snorkeling edition. We had the great opportunity to visit the MARS restoration projects in Badi and Bontosua Islands. We went snorkeling to see HOPE (literally and figuratively) under the sea.</p>
<p>Try and visit Google Earth and search for this HOPE.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3925" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-800x445.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="445" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-200x111.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-300x167.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-400x223.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-600x334.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-768x428.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-800x445.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-1024x570.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-1200x668.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-1536x855.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-5B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Here is Lily Damayanti, Marine Program Manager of the Mars Sustainable Solutions (MARS) project, explaining to us the location of the HOPE reef. Our boats approaching Pulau Badi.</em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-20 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Friday &#8211; Day 5</span></strong></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya</strong></span></p>
<p>We had a chance to see the University Coral Collection and talk to local scientists about the coral biodiversity and state of reefs around Makassar. The rest of the day we discussed our projects with each other and with Indonesian colleagues and looked for potential collaboration opportunities.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-21 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3937" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6A-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Mariya’s joy of seeing new branching coral samples in UNHAS collection</em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-22 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-23 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 5: 0730H</p>
<p>Back to UNHAS for one day of roundtable discussions on international research collaborations. We spent most of our time in the afternoon networking among ourselves and being updated with each and everyone’s research progress. We also spent some time working on project synthesis and collaborative work among the ESRs. We had a nice impromptu visit to the UNHAS coral museum where we saw their coral collections. Dinner (Coto Makassar) then some karaoke after.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3926" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-800x1040.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="1040" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-200x260.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-231x300.jpg 231w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-400x520.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-600x780.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-768x998.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-788x1024.jpg 788w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-800x1040.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-1182x1536.jpg 1182w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-1200x1559.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-scaled.jpg 1477w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-6B-1576x2048.jpg 1576w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Most of the discussions were behind closed doors, so better share with you our dinner (Coto Makassar) and activity that night, karaoke! </em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-24 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Saturday &#8211; Day 6</strong></span></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya</strong></span></p>
<p>Visiting reef sites again!</p>
<p>Cats, cats, cats everywhere on Kodingareng Keke. And great view onto the reef structure from the observation point &#8211; you can even see the seasonal sediment dynamics patterns, change in coral cover between reef flat and slope. Also, the island has pretty interesting history of unsuccessful commercialising of the area and failed efforts of the hotel construction. All in all &#8211; no wonder it did not work &#8211; the island is very dynamic, small and has no fresh water!</p>
<p>Samalona island – one of the closest to the shore, turbid reef. To our surprise, the coral cover was amazing, considering a lot of it was absent some 10 years ago! In some areas of the reef, coral cover was up to 95%, so we had to be careful swimming around.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-25 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3938" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-800x789.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="789" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-66x66.jpg 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-200x197.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-300x296.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-400x394.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-600x592.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-768x757.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-800x789.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-1024x1010.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-1200x1183.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-1536x1514.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A_-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3927" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-800x640.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="640" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-177x142.jpg 177w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-200x160.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-300x240.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-400x320.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-600x480.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-768x614.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-800x640.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-1024x819.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-1200x960.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-1536x1229.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7A-b_resized-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Above: Kodingareng Keke – seasonally dynamic island sediment accumulation area – and its local cats (quadrant for scale). Hi from 4D – REEF! Xin, Max, Leo, and Mariya.<br />
</em><em>Lower pictures: The beauty of the reef world. Top left &#8211; Tridacna squamosa, top right &#8211; a family of clown fish in sea anemone, surrounded by massive Porites; bottom left &#8211; sponge Haliclona sp. growing on sea star, bottom right &#8211; Acroporidae corals, branching and corymbose morphologies. </em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-26 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-27 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 6: 0700H</p>
<p>Field day again! This time we visited select reef sites in Samalona and Kodingareng Keke. We snorkeled and looked at the conditions of the reefs in both sites.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-fusion-800 wp-image-3928" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-7B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Estra checking out the condition of a coral in one of the reef sites.</em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-28 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Sunday &#8211; Day 7</strong></span></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Mariya</strong></span></p>
<p>As for my day off &#8211; no rest for the wicked! Starting at 7am, I joined our little crew to collect some sediment samples for future composition analysis of grains with the AI, developed by our colleague, William Harrison. We returned to Kodingareng Keke for the transect sampling across the reef flat. In the areas closer to the rim it got really tricky, as there was so much coral cover that I barely could get some sand!</p>
<p>Things were more complicated in the degraded turbid reef site &#8211; strong current, no coral is sight and fields of sea urchins. I got deserved rest and a great recovery after swimming for so long with a relaxing massage by Indonesian masters and enjoying another tasty dinner and fruit drinks. Everyone has to try sirsak! And if you are weak to spicy food &#8211; it will save you &#x1f642; To continue with the first experiences &#8211; I joined guys for the evening karaoke &#8211; something I have never done before but now will definitely do again!</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-29 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-fusion-800 wp-image-3939" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo8A-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Discovering the coral diversity. </em></p>
<div class="fusion-builder-row fusion-builder-row-inner fusion-row"><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-30 fusion_builder_column_inner_1_3 1_3 fusion-one-third fusion-column-first" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:30.6666%; margin-right: 4%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy"><div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div><div class="fusion-layout-column fusion_builder_column_inner fusion-builder-nested-column-31 fusion_builder_column_inner_2_3 2_3 fusion-two-third fusion-column-last" style="--awb-bg-size:cover;width:65.3333%;"><div class="fusion-column-wrapper fusion-column-has-shadow fusion-flex-column-wrapper-legacy">
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Katt</strong></span></p>
<p>Day 7: 0600H</p>
<p>It was our rest day, but I decided to visit an older carbonate reef in South Sulawesi. Whole day of travel, yet I enjoyed it since I was joined by very helpful and dependable Indonesian marine researchers.</p>
<div class="fusion-clearfix"></div></div></div></div>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-fusion-800 wp-image-3929" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-800x600.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="600" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Photo-8B-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Nice view of the beach and terraces to cap off the week in South Sulawesi.</em></p>
<p>Whole-day seminars, informative presentations, chats in-between coffee breaks and lunches, long-hours of discussions, site visits on reef islands, snorkeling on different reefs, fun chats while walking, and several boat rides. Endless coconuts, hotel rooftop drinks, occasional massages, souvenir shopping, lovely food, getting soaked by rain, soaking in the pool, karaoke, and long catching-up chats.</p>
<p>From participating in various program-related activities to enjoying non-program-related activities, the ESRs, our Indonesian colleagues, and supervisors had a very productive NTA in Makassar.</p>
<p>The first week of the NTA was very insightful as we were updated about the latest state of marine research, management, and conservation efforts in Indonesia. We found it inspiring to see the MARS success story and the different marine research work in Indonesia. The marine pollution problem (which is caused by a multitude of factors like government in/action, local behavior, heavy plastic use, and many others) in the region is quite noticeable along the coastal areas and offshore islands. As part of the ESRs who were not able to join the fieldwork in Spermonde, it was nice for us to visit the reefs studied by 4D-REEF.</p>
<p>Next up, we’ll share some of our experiences when we flew to Bali Island for the second part of our NTA. Stay tuned.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>*All photos made by 4D-Reef and ESRs.</p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reef Digital Twins</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/digital-twins/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 16:54:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Digital Twin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roberto Giudici]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3733</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by Roberto Giudici, ESR of 4D-REEF at OceanMaps in Austria.   Scientific descriptions of reefs contain a wealth of information, but are difficult to communicate in a form that can be easily understood by the general public. Digital Twins programs have recently been introduced for assisting scientific communities in data fostering and outreach, turning]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by Roberto Giudici, ESR of 4D-REEF at OceanMaps in Austria.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Scientific descriptions of reefs contain a wealth of information, but are difficult to communicate in a form that can be easily understood by the general public. Digital Twins programs have recently been introduced for assisting scientific communities in data fostering and outreach, turning complex experiments into pleasant stories. Born for creating digital models of industrial scenarios, these solutions are emerging as educational tools in science.  I, ESR Roberto, ventured in the development of an educational Digital Twin, showing the reconstruction of a reef on a coralline beach, in form of 3D immersive Serious Game, featuring images and descriptions of the corals and their state of health.</p>
<p>The blog contains links to download two developed Digital Twins (<a href="https://omg-share-frankfurt.s3.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/4d-reef/4d-reef_showcase_installer.exe">link 1</a> and <a href="https://omg-share-frankfurt.s3.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/4d-reef/Kodingareng_Keke_Giudici.zip">link 2</a>)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>What is a Digital Twin</strong></p>
<p>A Digital twin is a technology that allows scientists to create a virtual replica of a physical object or system. This replica can be used to simulate the behaviour of the physical object or system, and can fit a wide range of applications. Digital Twins have the potential to revolutionize the way scientists and researchers study and understand complex any dynamic Earth&#8217;s processes, bridging the gaps between research and dissemination and harnessing specialist expertise in topographic modelling with interactive maps.</p>
<p>Roberto modelled two Digital Twins; an entire coralline island scenario, similar as in the Spermonde field study area, featuring vegetation, sandy beach, coral reef and fish, to virtually unveil the secrets of this fascinating environment and describe its processes.</p>
<p><strong><br />
Digital Twin developed for turbid reef visualisation</strong></p>
<p>The development of a Digital Twin of a selected reef at the Spermonde archipelago, required the creation of a fully interactive 3D replica of the most relevant entities, featuring the creation of a topographic map of the seabed and emerged islands, a set of layers of ancillary information, including photographic, descriptions, etc. The resulting scenario would be presented into 3D immersive form, to let the user diving in a virtual reef, plounging the user in the beauty of the underwater world helping raising awarness about these endangered ecosystems. I decided to target an audience of young students, showing them the reefs as games, as proposed by several ESRs and supervisors from 4D-REEF.</p>
<p>I chose to develop the Digital Twins with Unity 3D, a market leading 3D Advanced Gaming Engine. Unity 3D is multiplatform and Multi Target, allowing to generate PC, Tablet, and Web based Gaming solutions at once. Moreover, this engine features an extremely large Repository of 3D objects and Terrains, including, vegetation, rocks, buildings, fish and other underwater animated species that can dynamically be added to our scenes to create more realistic scenes. The terrain can be either digitally synthetized through a terrain generator application to create pseudo-random topographic and morphological features, or we can import existing terrains, issued of Topo-Bathymetric surveys. In this latter case, the original terrain will be first composed by a 3D Point-Cloud and has to be converted into a 3D Mesh, through an operation called Triangulation. The terrain needs to be georeferenced during acquisition or Post Processing, with Geographical Coordinates issued of a GPS receiver.</p>
<p><strong><br />
Digital Twins Use cases: Focus on CAO, BIM and GIS</strong></p>
<p>Digital Twins have so far mainly been used for industrial applications, providing substantial assistance in industry and construction.  Seabed mapping and benthic classification developed only when reliable Multibeam Echo-Sounders and Underwater Laserscans came into market. Newer fully interoperable 3D engines are leveraging on advanced parallel computing to offer a fully immersive and interactive experience, based on first person’s view, where the users can freely navigate in virtual ocean depths and reach inaccessible regions, straight from their home’s pc screen. I tried to first characterise some potential applications of a Digital Twin of the Spermonde Islands, and identified three main options, ordered by growing complexity:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>SCIENTIFIC DISSEMINATION TOOL:</strong> To visually and interactively make aspects of research insightful. Needs describing a mission of Research, by its geographical locations, position and type of Sampling operated on the site, Georeferenced Clickable Images and Pop-Up windows with Explanations. This model corresponds to navigable 3D Hypertext, with limited interoperability and realm. It cannot be used for simulations or serious games.</li>
<li><strong>MARINE/COASTAL INFORMATION MANAGEMENT SYSTEM (MIMS/CIMS):</strong> This corresponds to the transposition in 3D of a GIS system connected to Geographical Data Bases for Real-Time Data Update. It features limited 3D navigability, but cannot be used for simulations, or serious games.</li>
<li><strong>SERIOUS GAME/SIMULATION:</strong> This is a fully immersive simulated Marine environment, featuring Coastal, Underwater and Benthic entities, such as Terrain, Sky, Clouds, Waves, Fish, Seagrass, Mangrove, Coral, Rocks and CAO entities such as Pipelines, ROVS, etc. It can feature advanced simulation of the underlying processes and manipulations (operating a ROV in a Pipe Deployment/Inspection mission. Physics Laws may be applied on the natural and CAO entities, to model the behaviour of Coastal Erosion due to underwater sedimentary transport, the Zooplacton Daily Vertical Migration (DVM) in the water column. The Laws of physics may extend to Weather conditions, light and colour absorption in the water Colum and reflection from the seabed. This latter scenario may also dynamically model the natural Spawn of Corals, Sea grass and fish swimming in schools driven by Social Algorithms (Algorithm of the Boids), with different types of realm depending of the Targeted Academic/Industrial/Retail community, and the Target Device (Mobile Device, PC, Web, etc.…). One or more characters driven by user interaction or pseudo random (or AI) cinematics, may also be added, featuring First Person Cameras (where the scene is seen from the eyes of the character), of Third Person Camera, where the User can see the entire scene (or a portion of it), independently of the movement of the characters. The realisation of this latter scenario may require an extensive amount of resources and a well-defined Project build on interactive participation of the Customer and the technical Teams. Based on the requirements, the cycle of production for this scenario may require several months of development.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Development Process</strong></p>
<p>I developed two Digital Twins. As Covid-19 travel restrictions prohibited the 4D-REEF ESRs from travelling to the Indonesian Spermonde archipelago, conducting bathymetric surveys in the field had to wait until summer 2022. Therefore I developed a pseudo-random Terrain using Gaia, one of the most advanced Generator working as Plugin from within the Unity Editor. This terrain would be replaced by the bathymetric maps of the Spermonde, once available.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>3D Scene Hierarchy in game engine Unity 3D</strong></p>
<p><strong>Scene:</strong> A 3D Scene is made up by a set of “Entities” that represent the abstraction of the Real World. The distances in a Scene are expressed in Points. Our Digital Twin has been developed in a Projected Georeferenced Space. The creation of a Georeferenced Space Layer of has been built by Ocean Maps, through a special customized application, as Unity 3D, being a 3D Gaming Engine, does not provide this Layer of Abstraction. The vegetation, rocks and Human crafted entities are all added to the Terrain. The Terrain, Cameras, Lighting, Sea, Weather, Sound, etc., are all attached to the Scene.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Terrain:</strong> This is the digital reconstruction of the soil, featuring, flat land, hills and mountains. It can be built as Pseudo-Random or imported an external 3D Mesh, normally obtained by Laserscan Photogrammetric or Bathymetric reconstructions. Unity 3D offers several cutting-edge Terrain Editors, like Gaia, used in this project.</li>
<li><strong> </strong><strong>Cameras:</strong> They represent the Viewport used by the user to see the terrain. They are defined by a Field Of View (FOV) that is the width of the region that can bene seen and its relative scale. They can be positioned freely by the user, and the FOV behaves as lenses of a real camera.</li>
<li><strong>Characters:</strong> They represent the main actors of the Serious Game and they can either be animated Humans, Animals, or Machines. They can have different levels of Animation.</li>
<li><strong>Lighting:</strong> Lighting sources are added to enlighten the scene and simulate real-environmental conditions. They can be freely deployed by the user, under Spot or Diffused, and beam width, direction and colour (light temperature) and their parameters can be changed during Run-Time.</li>
<li><strong>Sea, Weather, Sound, etc.:</strong> These entities are commonly used in Serious Games provide a better realm and user experience to the scene.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Digital Twin 1: Serious Game: Dive in the reef</span></strong></p>
<p>This Digital Twin can be downloaded <a href="https://omg-share-frankfurt.s3.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/4d-reef/4d-reef_showcase_installer.exe">here (link)</a>.</p>
<p>The process of creating a Digital Twin of a coralline island is illustrated by the pipeline shown at Fig. 1.  We decided to use the Gaia Terrain Generator that features a set of tools for creating all the entities required in the current project. The operations required for creating and populating the Terrain are shown at Fig. 2.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3736" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_1_resized.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="396" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_1_resized-200x158.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_1_resized-300x238.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_1_resized-400x317.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_1_resized.jpg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 1: Process of Island Generation</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3737" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="474" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-200x112.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-300x167.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-400x223.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-600x335.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-768x429.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized-800x447.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_2_resized_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 2: Pipeline for the creation of a Digital Twin for Dissemination</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Creation of the Terrain:</strong> The first step required the creation of a terrain featuring a tropical coralline sedimentary island. We created the terrain using a Stamp provided by the Gaia Editor (Fig. 3).<br />
<strong>Procedure for Generating a Coralline island: </strong>Gaia provides existing Stamps featuring the most common morphologies: Mountains, Flat Land,  Hills, Island, Archipelago, etc. However, custom Stamps can also be imported.</p>
<p><strong>Properties of the island:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Planimetry of the island is defined by a Stamp that can reproduce straight coastline, Bays, Gulfs, etc.).</li>
<li>Morphology of the Island: Elevation</li>
<li>Ruggedness: smooth, polished rock to rough crystalline</li>
<li>Topographic Discontinuities: Valleys, Graben, etc.</li>
<li>Sedimentary feature: Type and Grain size. Different grain types can be included and the transition to the different types can be set through linear or custom laws</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3738" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="434" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-200x102.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-300x153.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-400x204.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-600x307.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-768x393.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized-800x409.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_3_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 3: Creating a Pseudo-Random Island with UNITY 3D &#8211; Gaia</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Gaia generates patterns of sediment with different of Sedimentary Facies and Grain Size and Morphological Structures, featuring longshore ripples with different orientations and height. This allows building complex sedimentary architectures at once. Morphological structures can also be highly customised with Scars, Graben, etc. (Fig. 4, 5).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3739" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-300x153.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="153" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-200x102.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-300x153.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-400x204.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-600x306.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-768x391.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized-800x408.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_4_5_resized.jpg 820w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figures 4, 5: Pseudo Random Sedimentary Rugosity and Scars</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Vegetation: </strong>The origin of the plant 3D specimens had to be defined ahead of any addition. We needed to procure the right set of entities useful for the project on the Unity Asset Store (The Virtual Market where entities can be purchased and downloaded). As the Spermonde Islands are Coralline islands, with no volcanic, nor Karstic formations, we selected a coralline sand and lowered the topography to get a low-lying island. We chose the right assemblage of plants after studying the distribution of some coralline islands at the Spermonde, namely Samalona, Kodigareng Keke and Langkai.</p>
<p><strong>Spawning the Entity on the Terrain:</strong> The Spawning operation on Gaia allows adding dozens of hundreds of specimens at once, with different pseudo-random spatial distributions, densities, sizes and orientations. We spawned first the vegetation of the emerged and riparian regions, adding palm trees along the beach and trees at the centre of the island. As these islands are just a few meters above the level of the sea, rainwater cannot accumulate, and therefore, mangrove forests cannot develop. In a second time, we added the seagrass and coral in the underwater in-shore region, above the reef flat (Fig. 6). The entire reef will be then covered by water, whose level is set during the construction of the model and can be freely changed on runtime, to simulate tides. Our model did not include tides, as the Spermonde has a micro tidal regime with a total tidal amplitude of approximately 50 cm on spring tide.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3740" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_6_resized.jpg" alt="" width="593" height="308" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_6_resized-200x104.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_6_resized-300x156.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_6_resized-400x208.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_6_resized.jpg 593w" sizes="(max-width: 593px) 100vw, 593px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure </em><em>6</em><em>: Coral Assemblage</em></p>
<p><strong>Environmental and Weather Engines:</strong>  Simulate the water, with water level, water turbidity, water caustics, and waves, based on the direction and strength of the wind generated by the weather engine. We also simulated changes in Sun light penetration in the water column, based on changing weather conditions across time on the scene.</p>
<p><strong>Daylight:</strong> Based on the month, time and weather conditions, the environmental engine sets the sun position, height, intensity and light temperature, recreating stunning environmental conditions.<br />
The final assemblage featuring vegetation and coral (shown at Fig 7).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3741" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="539" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-200x127.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-300x190.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-320x202.jpg 320w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-400x254.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-600x381.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-768x488.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized-800x508.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_7_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 7: Final Terrain Assemblage</em></p>
<p><strong>Fish and underwater living forms: </strong>The addition of underwater forms of life like fish that move within the scene, is a challenging process. In particular, the computation of the positions of fish swimming in a school requires the implementation of Algorithms driving the Social Behaviour of fishes, like the Algorithm of the Boids that reproduces the Flocking behaviour of fish (Fig. 8).</p>
<p><strong>The algorithm for fish movement is composed of Four Rules:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Cohesion:</strong> Fish search for their neighbours in a radius defined as the Radius of Cohesion. The current positions of all neighbours are summed up. The result is divided by the number of neighbours. Thus, the centre of mass of the neighbours is obtained. This is the point to which the fish strive for cohesion.</li>
<li><strong>Separation:</strong> Fish search for their neighbours in a radius defined as the Separation Radius. To calculate the motion vector of an individual fish in a specific separation direction from a school, the difference in the positions of the neighbours and its own position is summed up. The result is divided by the number of neighbours and then normalized and multiplied by -1 to change the initial direction of the fish to swim in the opposite direction of the neighbours.</li>
<li><strong>Alignment:</strong> Fish search for their neighbours in a radius defined as the Radius of Alignment. The current speeds of all neighbours are summed, then divided by the number of neighbours.</li>
<li><strong>Reversal:</strong> All of the fish can only swim in a given space, the boundaries of which can be specified. The moment a fish crosses a boundary must be identified. If a fish hits a boundary, then the direction of the fish is changed to the opposite vector (thereby keeping the fish within the defined space). <em>(Source: Unreal 3D)</em></li>
</ol>
<p>The Flocking algorithm needed to be adapted to Pelagic and Benthic fishes like Grazers.</p>
<ul>
<li>Pelagic fish: Oceanic pelagic fish typically inhabit waters below the continental shelf.</li>
<li>Benthic fish: Fish that live on or near the sea-bottom, irrespective of the depth of the sea.</li>
</ul>
<p>As all existing solutions provided by game engine Unity 3D cannot yet integrate this distinction, we rewrote the algorithm to simulate the behaviour of Reef fish like Parrotfish, Clown fish, Surgeonfish. We implemented a Pseudo-Random variant of the algorithm, where the parameters and the target followed by the leader of the fish school change over time, to create a better realm. We applied different sets of parameters and social rules for each species of fish, to account for their social behaviour. The first developed the Algorithm of the Boids on an empty scene, to validate the behaviour of the fish swimming inside the boundaries of a Bounding Box Cube (Fig. 9). The fish continuously watch ahead to check the eventual presence of obstacles that must be avoided, diverging their routes or bouncing back (Fig. 11).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3742" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="338" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-200x80.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-300x119.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-400x159.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-600x239.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-768x306.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized-800x318.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_8_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 8: Social behaviour of fish and anticollision (coloured lines).</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3743" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="359" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-200x85.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-300x127.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-400x169.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-600x254.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-768x325.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized-800x338.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_9_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 9: Principle of the implementation of a Pseudo-Random Flocking Fish Algorithm.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3744" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="344" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-200x81.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-300x122.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-400x162.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-600x243.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-669x272.jpg 669w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-768x311.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized-800x324.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_10_11_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 10 (left): Social behaviour of fish and anticollision (coloured lines)<br />
Figure 11 (right): Behaviour of a herd of fish at the Bounding Box Boundary</em></p>
<p>As such we have produced a Digital Twin of the type of islands in the Spermonde Archipelago. We can eventually complete the scene with a Character that simulates the presence of a diver or of a marine mammal. Now we are ready to embed the data originated by surveying sampling missions conducted by the 4D-REEF ESRs. These datasets are mainly composed by a set of images and geographically pinpointed locations of coral and sedimentary samples. Their addition to the scene could give a direct overview of the works done on the site, and may be enriched with coral and benthic maps, or results of other custom animations. This first application is meant to be a fully featured baseline for further developments.</p>
<p><strong><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Digital Twin 2: 3D Coral Surveying at the Kodingareng Keke island</span></strong></p>
<p>This Digital Twin can be downloaded <a href="https://omg-share-frankfurt.s3.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/4d-reef/Kodingareng_Keke_Giudici.zip">here (link)</a>.</p>
<p>This second demo concerns the development of a 3D environment built on the bathymetric map gathered during a bathymetric surveying mission held at the island of Kodigareng Keke summer 2022. We conducted the survey using a Multibeam Echo Sounder (MBES), to gather a high-resolution map of the seabed, over the lagoon and the reef slope, on waters not shallower than 1 m, as our surveying boat could not navigate on the 50 cm shallow reef flat. The raw bathymetric Dataset has been produced as 3D dense Point Cloud form, featuring hundreds of points per square inch (Fig. 12). We post processed the Dataset, removed outlier points, and added the 3D Point Cloud in the Unity 3D Gaming Engine, to create a terrain. The Point Cloud shows clearly the reef slope and some sedimentary architectures that would not be visible through underwater or satellite images and may worth further investigations, to help disclosing the evolution of the coral platform. We then developed two different views that will be detailed hereafter:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Satellite View:</strong> We wrapped the 3D terrain with a satellite orthophotography of the island, to build a realistic model of its emerged and underwater regions (Fig. 13).</li>
<li><strong>Bathymetric View:</strong> In this latter view, we do not show any orthophotography of the islands, but we assign a scale of different colours for each different height, to give a better view of the depth of the seabed (Fig. 14).</li>
</ol>
<p>We also added some tools for measuring distances and depth.  The point (1), (2) and (3) at Fig. 15 show respectively the altitude of the island sand cay (51.58 m), the altitude at the middle of the reef slope (51.06 m) and the altitude at the lagoon (41,87 m). These values have been computed above the average altitude of the Reference Geoid used to calibrate the Bathymetric map. Underwater images have been shot at some spotted points along long-shore and cross-shore transects (point (4).</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3745" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="472" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-200x111.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-300x167.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-400x222.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-600x334.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-768x427.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized-800x445.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_12_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 12: Original Point Cloud at Kodigareng Keke.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3746" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="463" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-200x109.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-300x164.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-400x218.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-600x327.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-768x419.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized-800x436.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_13_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 13: 3D Satellite reconstruction of Kodigareng Keke.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3747" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="453" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-200x107.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-300x160.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-400x213.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-600x320.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-768x410.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized-800x427.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure_14_resized.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Figure 14: 3D Bathymetric reconstruction of Kodigareng Keke.</em></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>I developed two Digital Twin solutions to help the scientific community develop novel tools for communicating science. We utilized some of the latest technologies, to create 3D realistic scenarios that can be extended for any educational purpose, ranging from 3D viewer to advanced Serious Games with first person view.  I always kept in mind that my product must be able to describe science through visual experiences and images, turning the scientific questions, contributions and results to pleasant interactives stories. Contributing to make science easy and understandable by communities of young students, should help them gathering a better comprehension of the marine life and promote their active participation to ongoing projects of research.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Further developments</strong></p>
<p>The program could be extended to other islands of the Spermonde archipelago, to create a wider scenario and simulating the coral and sedimentary transport between islands. The current demo could be turned into a Serious Game based on the construction of a Reef, where the students would build and maintain their own reef.</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Roberto-Giudici-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2733"><span class="esr-link">Roberto Giudici</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Computer Science, MSc in Geomorphological Science</p>
	<p>Ocean Maps GmbH, Austria</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Adventure at the AGU fall meeting 2022</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/agu-adventure/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 17:45:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Xin Ren]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3722</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by Xin Ren, PhD student of 4D-REEF at the University of Bristol in the UK.   AGU (American Geophysical Union) Fall Meeting is one of the biggest conferences in the area of Earth and space sciences. This year it was hosted in Chicago. More than 25,000 attendees from over 100 countries gathered and shared]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by Xin Ren, PhD student of 4D-REEF at the University of Bristol in the UK. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>AGU (American Geophysical Union) Fall Meeting is one of the biggest conferences in the area of Earth and space sciences. This year it was hosted in Chicago. More than 25,000 attendees from over 100 countries gathered and shared their latest research results in this conference. I (Xin) brought part of 4D-REEF to AGU22.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><u>A new environment of hybrid conference</u></strong></p>
<p>Since the impact of COVID-19 still exists, AGU offered virtual and in-person attendance this year, as it did last year. In the conference hall, the organizer provided not only masks but also lanyard with different colours to show our preferred comfortable distance level. They really did a great job.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3725" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte.png" alt="" width="849" height="478" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-200x113.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-300x169.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-400x225.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-600x338.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-768x432.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte-800x450.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig1_aangepast-grootte.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Fig1. Left: Mask provided by the host with the “AGU” mark on it. That helped me to recognize the AGU attendees on the train. Middle: Lanyard that shows your preferred distance level. Right: Me in the conference hall.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I tried the virtual meeting platform because I felt ill for the first 2 days. For virtual attendance, we could join live sessions and post our interactive comments during talks. It was very convenient and efficient. We could also customize and build our own schedules and find all the information via the platform. Although there were so many sessions and themes, it was still easy and clear to locate the presentation you were interested in and add them to your schedule. Besides, you won’t miss out on any presentation or discussion because most sessions have been recorded and the recordings are still available (which makes the registration fee so worth it to me). With the adoption of various online tools, we can have more options for meetings in the future; the limitations of time, distance, and other accessibility will have less and less impact to researchers.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3726" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte.png" alt="" width="849" height="478" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-200x113.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-300x169.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-400x225.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-600x338.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-768x432.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte-800x450.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig2_aangepast-grootte.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Fig2: Top left: In-person meeting room. Bottom left: Online meeting with live subtitles on. Right: Meeting platform interface.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><u>My poster presentation</u></strong></p>
<p>For us early stage researchers, the poster session was a good opportunity to chat and meet researchers who have the same research interests. In the poster session, I presented my work on the hydrological cycle and ocean circulation of the Maritime Continent in the mid-Pliocene and received some interesting comments from other researchers. Recently, this work has been posted as preprint under review for Climate of the Past, which you can access <a href="https://egusphere.copernicus.org/preprints/2022/egusphere-2022-1281/">here (link)</a>. The preprint is a preliminary version of a scientific paper that is posted online prior to formal peer-review and publication so that all the readers, not just reviewers, can comment on it and help improve the paper before publication. By the way, we are still open for comments until 1st February 2023. Welcome to post your comments.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3727" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte.png" alt="" width="849" height="478" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-200x113.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-300x169.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-400x225.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-600x338.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-768x432.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte-800x450.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig3_aangepast-grootte.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Fig3. Top left: I met Dr. Heather at Queen Mary University of London. Top right: I was presenting my work to a small group who were interested in the climate of the mid-Pliocene. Bottom left: scan the QR code to post comments on my preprint paper. Bottom right: look at the red mark which is the symbol of our 4D-REEF.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>During my poster session, I met researchers in my network. I also met some new researchers who were interested in my work. The most interesting thing was that when I discussed the currents in the western tropical Pacific, someone mentioned a record which I could probably use to support my future work. Turns out that the person who works on this record was someone I previously met at a workshop in the UK. Such a small world of paleoclimate studying.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><u>Other activities &amp; Snowy Chicago</u></strong></p>
<p>The conference offered many other activities such as fieldworks, scientific skill development sessions, exhibitions, etc.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3728" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte.png" alt="" width="849" height="510" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-200x120.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-300x180.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-400x240.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-600x360.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-768x461.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte-800x481.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin_Fig4_aangepast-grootte.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Fig4. NASA booth in the exhibition hall. The presentation of the James Webb Space Telescope was very popular.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>On the last day of the AGU22 meeting, it was snowing in Chicago. Here are some nice photos of the snowy Chicago scene.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3730" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-scaled.jpeg" alt="" width="874" height="175" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-200x40.jpeg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-300x60.jpeg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-400x80.jpeg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-600x120.jpeg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-768x154.jpeg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-800x160.jpeg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-1024x205.jpeg 1024w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-1200x240.jpeg 1200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-1536x307.jpeg 1536w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Fig5-scaled.jpeg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 874px) 100vw, 874px" /></p>
<p><em>Fig5. Some beautiful snowy views of Lake Michigan next to the conference hall.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Xin-Ren-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-1-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2747"><span class="esr-link">Xin Ren</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Quaternary Geology</p>
	<p>University of Bristol, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>4D-Reef at the 15th International Coral Reef Symposium</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/4d-reef-at-the-15th-international-coral-reef-symposium/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 13:18:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fursman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3697</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Where do we even begin, it's the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where do we even begin, it&#8217;s the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog post. (For those clueless about our awful joke see Fig. 1c; self-explanatory hopefully &#x1f605;?). This event was also the first ever climate neutral ICRS. Anyway, strap in and prepare to hear about how we schooled (another reef joke!!) for a week with fellow reef enthusiasts in the charming city of Bremen, northern Germany.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3708 " src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png" alt="" width="382" height="554" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-200x290.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-207x300.png 207w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-400x579.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-600x869.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png 707w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-768x1112.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1: <strong>a):</strong> The “Town Musicians of Bremen” &#8211; a Grimm’s fairy tale about a group of aging animals who move to Bremen to become musicians and their stack is an unofficial symbol of the city. <strong>b): </strong>The opening ceremony of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS. <strong>c)</strong> A blue-spotted cornet fish (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fistularia_commersonii">Fistularia commersonii)</a>.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>ICRS usually happens every four years and, after the 2021 edition was turned into a virtual meeting due to the pandemic, the wilds of humanity descended upon the delayed in-person event in order to (while following all health and safety protocols) socialise and discuss all things reef! This cosmopolitan single event had more than 1500 attendees coming from more than 170 countries across the globe, joining online and in-person. 4D-Reef was well represented, coming from across Europe to join with our endemic Bremenites who were helping to organise the event.</p>
<p>Those Bremen-based 4D-Reefers present were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Daniel Schürholz (Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Arjun Chennu (Max-Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Estradivari (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Sebastian Ferse (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Kathrine Maxwell (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
</ul>
<p>Honestly, each one of them deserves their own round of applause and their own blog post for that matter, as they have been central to the organisation and success of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS and all behind-the-scenes perks. To all the Bremen 4D-Reefers, we would like to express our gratitude and admiration on behalf of all our colleagues. They have gone to extreme lengths, chaired sessions, organised side events, led visits to their institutes and on top of all that also presented their own research at ICRS. Hats off to you guys!!</p>
<p>The 4D reef delegation was not just composed of endemic folks. We had a significant representation of 4D-Reefers from all over the place who made their way to Bremen to give either poster or oral presentations (check the official tweet from 4D-Reef and the various threads for more deets and super dooper sciency pics and embarrassing moments too &#8211; yeah there was a party in the end and yeah we shook it all off till we bleached). As part of the visiting delegation, we had:</p>
<ul>
<li>Leo Bertini (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Bristol)</li>
<li>Max Fursman (Goethe University Frankfurt)</li>
<li>Andrew Torres (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
<li>Kenneth Johnson (The Natural History Museum)</li>
<li>Erica Hendy (University of Bristol)</li>
<li>William Harrison (Naturalis Biodiversity Centre &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
</ul>
<p>If you&#8217;d like to have a glimpse at what each of them have been up to, please check out the <a href="https://www.icrs2022.de/fileadmin/user_upload/ICRS2022_BookOfAbstracts_July2.pdf">Official Conference Book of Abstracts</a> by searching their names.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3721 size-fusion-800" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png" alt="" width="800" height="405" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-200x101.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-300x152.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-400x203.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-540x272.png 540w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-600x304.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-768x389.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2: All the 4D-Reef PhDs hard at work, presenting posters, talks and their equipment.</em><br />
<em><strong><u>Top row</u></strong><u>:</u>  <strong>Daniel</strong> proudly stands next to his Hyper Diver holding up the information posters, waiting to ambush anyone passing by and tell them all about the wonderous imaging that can be done.<strong> Andrew</strong> gleefully discusses his work at his poster during the poster sessions, enthralling a passer-by with his knowledge. <strong><u>Middle row</u></strong>:<strong> Kat</strong> dazzles the crowd with her talk on coral reef terraces, scattering pictures of her fieldwork in the Philippines throughout to make us jealous! <strong>Estra </strong>educates everyone on MPAs and the emergence of OECMs and their benefits. <strong>Max </strong>doesn’t clam up as he discusses Tridacna shell chemistry! <strong><u>Bottom row</u></strong>: <strong>Leo </strong>has captured a CT lover and is busy discussing the ins and outs of coral scanning. <strong>Will </strong>wows those nearby with his remarks on changing coral reef habitats.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Face to face is important: strengthening connections and accelerating collabs</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a fantastic opportunity for us to present our work to the reef community, and many of the 4D-Reefers had posters and talks at the conference. It was such a nice change of pace to be able to chat to people face to face about science and answer questions from them over a second glass of wine or third bagel. Some of us got to meet up with colleagues from previous endeavours, be it our masters or other research projects. But more importantly got to meet new people, discuss new ideas for research and potential collaborations. We were able to expand our network through our current peers, including friends we’ve been working in close collaboration with from Cardiff University, Imperial College London, Malaysia, Singapore and Frankfurt, as they acted as match makers and introduced us to their own networks.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3710 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png" alt="" width="566" height="471" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-200x167.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-300x250.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-600x500.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-768x640.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-800x666.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3: Leo reuniting with and meeting new people.<strong> a)</strong> Dear friends Catie, Dom Brown and Luigi whom I worked with during my MSc looking at how reefs in Chagos have endured since the 2015 mass bleaching event. <strong>b)</strong> A fellow Brazilian ICRS attendee, Gabriel Cardoso, a PhD at Frei University Berlin looking at coral geochemical records. I met Gabriel in person after having read from his latest and outstanding work investigating how reefs in the Abrolhos bank were impacted by turbidity caused by mining refuse following the collapse of the Fundão dam, considered the biggest environmental disaster in Brazilian history, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969721059581">more here</a>. <strong>c) </strong>A prosecco with Sara Todorovic by my poster. Sara and her supervisor Dr Henry Wu, from ZMT, have been my collaborators. They look at geochemical signatures in coral cores from which I am automating the retrieval of growth rates and coral endobiont metrics.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3711 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png" alt="" width="560" height="563" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-66x66.png 66w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-150x150.png 150w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-200x201.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-600x603.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-768x772.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4: Social gatherings. <strong>a and</strong> <strong>d) </strong>The members of 4D-Reef and associates gathered for a beer and food after a hard day of conferencing! <strong>b)</strong> Allia Rosedy, our Malaysian associate, munching on a pretzel tree. <strong>c)</strong> Polyp Leo overheating and expelling his zooxanthellae while showing his moves to the beat of ABBA. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>The first climate neutral ICRS ever</strong><br />
Given how our reefs have been suffering in the face of anthropogenic pressures, the least we can do to halt global warming is to try and minimize our everyday carbon footprints and this was the mindset behind every single aspect of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS.</p>
<p>For instance, attendees were given free public transport around town, thus encouraging a greener way of mass mobility (our badges acted as public transport passes – how clever of you people!). When it comes to food during either coffee breaks or lunches, catering was also well thought-out and vegetarian (we, being a Brazilian and an Irish, were suspicious of this, given our white-tip-shark-like instincts for blood – another reef joke, it’s been a while). But honestly, food was so outstandingly tasty that we welcomed the menu like sea anemones welcome clown fish.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-fusion-200 wp-image-3712 aligncenter" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="141" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-300x212.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-400x283.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-600x424.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-768x543.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-800x565.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 5: Post-lunch break in the ICRS poster lounge. That was the best place to chill and recover from our food comas after lunch (left to right: Max, Leo and Andrew- not so satiated apparently?).</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Another striking aspect from catering was that priority was given for seasonal and local produce and the next day’s menu included ingredients used the day before to reduce food waste. Speaking of waste, this year there was rarely a flyer or physical promotional goodies around (let’s be honest those often end up forgotten in drawers). The entire programme was available to attendees via a web application, with real time announcements, chat, polling, and social functionalities. Attendees were also encouraged to bring their own liquid containers for drinking water and paper cups were offered as a better alternative to plastic.</p>
<p>Of course, it is impossible to actively reduce our carbon footprint to zero over such a short amount of time. There were energy costs for ventilating the venue, electricity, participant overseas travel emissions and other essentials that we cannot give up on (after all, we will never be as resourceful and energy efficient as corals). For this, organisers used part of the fees to purchase carbon credits equivalent of 1.491 tons of carbon emissions. The purchase is regulated by a third company who ensures measures are put into place to neutralize our carbon footprints following the UN environment programme and the Kyoto protocol.</p>
<p><strong>Our retrospective</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a wonderful opportunity to not only showcase the incredible work we’ve been doing as part of 4D-Reef and to bring awareness of how important turbid reefs are, but also to get new perspectives and connect with an amazing swarm of both young and well-established scientists from across multiple fields.</p>
<p>The conference was an opportunity to celebrate our endurance over the hardship the pandemic has brought onto the community, both as a whole and for some at deeply personal levels. Throughout the event, we shared (and vented – because we’re all human) about how we managed to stay afloat through such murky times. There was a moment to remember all the loved ones we lost along the way since the last in-person ICRS. May we continue their legacy and make the remaining reefs proud of what we do to protect the oceans!</p>
<p>The 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS has definitely set the bar high for any upcoming conferences. We already look forward to the ingenuity that will come with the 16<sup>th</sup> ICRS, which will be in New Zealand (i.e., land of Erica, land of the kiwis and the Maori).</p>
<p>Ka kite ano, ICRS!</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Max-Fursman-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2743"><span class="esr-link">Max Fursman</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy and Biodiversity</p>
	<p>Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scientific Dive Course Part 2: Electric Boogaloo</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/scientific-dive-course-part-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 12:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3674</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“Tam” Towels on the dive course. This is what we call surfing towels after 4D-REEF team member Tamara Stuij. Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.   Blog by Mike Hynes, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center.   We survived! After a very intense three weeks, working weekends and late into the evening, I am]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“Tam” Towels on the dive course. This is what we call surfing towels after 4D-REEF team member Tamara Stuij. Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.  </em></p>
<p><em>Blog by Mike Hynes, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We survived! After a very intense three weeks, working weekends and late into the evening, I am happy to report that Flo-D REEF (4D-REEF and our fellow dive course member Flo, who works on super cool fish from the Caribbean called hamlets. Also I am hoping my new underwater symbol for hamlets catches on) have all passed the European Scientific Dive Course (German Edition run by our consortium affiliate institution ZMT, more info <a href="https://www.leibniz-zmt.de/en/research-infrastructure/scientific-diving-centre.html">here</a>). Though some of us still need to get a lifeguard certificate before receiving the official Scientific Certification, but that’s just a formality (I hope. Fingers crossed). Los Gigantes, Tenerife in the Canary Islands was the home of our latest 4D-REEF adventure.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3683" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2.png" alt="" width="844" height="419" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-200x99.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-300x149.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-400x199.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-600x298.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-768x381.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-800x397.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2.png 844w" sizes="(max-width: 844px) 100vw, 844px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1 – All of us on the boat ready to practice the swim test. Image courtesy of Andreas Kunzmann.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I will not lie, this course was difficult (like real difficult. Far surpassing any of my previous dive courses, including my Dive Master), full of paperwork and homework (to the German standards of course), and despite a lot of last minute organization, we managed to get the most out of it. In no small part because we got to go to sunny and beautiful Tenerife. Here we learned important skills like dive operation planning and teamwork: adequately assessing risks, mitigating them, and devising a strategy to quickly and safely conduct our underwater research. Safety and rescue drills galore were done to prepare us to deal with a variety of issues that can happen to divers (such as entanglements, heart attacks, decompression illness, and more).  And we even got to test out a cool scientific method called the Hyper Diver (stay tuned to learn about this). We also had an opportunity to bond (something about the bonding power of shared suffering or something like that) and spend time together as (part of) the consortium, something that has been lacking due to corona and travel restrictions. This is evident as even after 3 weeks of diving, most of us went on a fun dive to just enjoy diving together (and a reward for all our hard work). Well, that and we wanted to check out some of the other dive sites on the island that we didn’t have a chance to get to on the course (not that Octopus Cove wasn’t a nice spot, but after 3 weeks of only diving there, a different set of scenery was appreciated).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3678" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="637" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2 – Five of us on a fun dive after we passed the exam. Image courtesy of Andrew Torres.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Now to the science part. We had to do a scientific project whilst diving as part of the course. I mentioned the Hyper Diver earlier and it is a cool tool that is being used by one of our ESR’s, Daniel Schürholz. Meeting at La Paella Rustica (NOT Daniel’s favorite restaurant) we learned all about this cool technique. Daniel then trusted us with a piece of equipment worth more than everything I own (but Daniel loves me enough to trust me, and I guess the others too).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3696" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit.png" alt="" width="840" height="354" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-200x84.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-300x126.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-400x169.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-600x253.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-768x324.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-800x337.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit.png 840w" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3 – Left: Dino Ramos using the Hyper Diver, therefore becoming ‘Hyper Dino’. Image courtesy of </em><em>Daniel Schürholz and Estradivari. Right: The supermarket chain in The Canaries ALSO named Hiperdino </em><em>(And which we are certain our Dino makes money from, but he still wouldn’t give us a discount). Image </em><em>courtesy of Hiperdino’s webpage.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>So I won’t get too bogged down into details as I know Daniel has recently written a <a href="/4D-REEF/coral-reef-habitat-mapping-in-corona-times">blog</a> explaining this WAAAYYY better than I ever could. Ostensibly, the Hyper Diver has 4 cameras, 2 standard RGB cameras and 2 cameras that are hyperspectral/multispectral (capturing more wavelengths then we can see with the human eye). There are also sensors like depth, altitude, light, pH, and more, to help calibrate the images being created. I am sure Daniel is internally screaming at me for saying something wrong, but basically we do this to create 3D topography images of the sea floor, and also to determine what animal communities/species are present. So by all of us doing this we have helped Daniel collect some data for his project from a new region with different organisms living here. And by having so many different operators, he can assess if repeatability between users is at a good level. So another useful output from our diving course has been the use of the Hyper Diver, and its data.<img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3501" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-4-1-1.gif" alt="" width="632" height="406" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4 – A 3D topographic model produced in Tenerife of the sea floor using Hyper Diver iamges. </em><em>Image courtesy of Daniel Schürholz.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Finally, thanks to the <a href="https://www.divingtenerife.co.uk/">diveshop </a>and its staff (Shiela, Paul, Sam, Neville, Chris, and Josh) for helping us through this course and taking us on a fun dive. Also, I would be remiss if I didn’t mention our favorite places that made Los Gigantes a great time; Berry’s ice cream (the guanábana ice cream was the best flavor. Don’t @ me), La Sangria, of course La Paella Rustica, and Highland Paddy’s (home of nightly karaoke and the ‘One Woman Band’ Solange. Incredible night. You had to be there. Trust me).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3680" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="637" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-200x150.jpg 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-300x225.jpg 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-400x300.jpg 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-600x450.jpg 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-768x576.jpg 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-800x600.jpg 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /><br />
<em>Figure 5 – Having a lovely dinner at La Paella Rustica before Daniel takes his expensive Hyper Diver away from us (for good reasons). Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.</em></p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Coral reef habitat mapping in Corona times</title>
		<link>/4D-REEF/coral-reef-habitat-mapping-in-corona-times/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 08:49:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daniel Schürholz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[habitat mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[machine learning]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/4D-REEF/?p=3637</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by Daniel Christoph Schürholz, PhD student of 4D-REEF at the Max-Planck-Institute for Marine Microbiology.   The current global pandemic has affected all of our personal and professional lives. I myself started my PhD project two and a half years ago with quite a different plan than what ended up playing out. Especially the field]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by Daniel Christoph Schürholz, PhD student of 4D-REEF at the Max-Planck-Institute for Marine Microbiology. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The current global pandemic has affected all of our personal and professional lives. I myself started my PhD project two and a half years ago with quite a different plan than what ended up playing out. Especially the field work in the Spermonde Archipelago in Indonesia has been repeatedly scratched off the calendar, and no certain schedule is yet in place, despite the great efforts of the organization committee. But we adapt, and with a good and supportive team of colleagues we find ways to produce interesting results in these difficult times. Luckily, this has also been the case in my PhD project, in which we are using previously collected datasets and “plastic” coral reefs to continue developing our coral reef surveying tools.</p>
<p><b>The evolution of underwater coral reef monitoring</b></p>
<p>For a bit of context: my project has the aim of surveying the seafloor communities in coral reefs. Underwater surveying started with ecologists visually identifying the organisms they encountered as they dived along the coral reefs. This process is still used in certain studies, because of the detailed descriptions. However, it is a slow process and heavily dependent on the expert’s knowledge of the local flora and fauna, with different experts focusing on some organisms more than others, or just lacking the experience to make a detailed assessment. To tackle these issues, scientists started using underwater photography to speed things up and quickly scan the seafloor. They do so by taking images of rectangular plastic frames overlaid on the reef floor. Then with image annotation software, experts give labels to randomly sampled points (generally between 5 and 25) on dozens or hundreds of the images. The percentage cover of different organisms in the reef is then calculated (i.e. corals cover 20% of this reef and sponges cover 5%). This method is called point count and is widely used in ecological surveys of the seafloor. But what we are missing with these surveying techniques is a detailed spatial representation of the organisms, their surroundings and their distribution. In other words we are missing a thematic habitat map of the seafloor. It is similar to describing a country only by the percentage of the world’s landmass it covers (i.e. Canada – 6.1%, India – 2.0%, Peru – 0.9%), instead of producing a geopolitical map that shows the sizes and shapes of countries, their access to bodies of water or neighboring countries. The analyses you could do with both methods are quite different.</p>
<p>With this in mind, researchers are using state-of-the-art technologies to automatically produce maps of terrestrial and marine habitats. Recent improvements in underwater photography, for example, with new diver operated devices, remotely operated vehicles and autonomous underwater vehicles , are producing a massive stream of new image data of underwater environments, such as coral reefs. Furthermore, structure-from-motion software enables stitching these underwater images together to form large and uninterrupted top-down views of the seafloor, called orthomosaics. However, to transform all these images and orthomosaics into habitat maps, experts still have to manually contour all organisms and objects in the images, then identify them and finally assign labels to them. This is a critical bottleneck in underwater monitoring and thus automating the map production process in a scalable manner is a necessity. Here enters machine learning (ML), more specifically, supervised learning. In supervised learning, an algorithm teaches computers to recognize certain patterns in the images (from textures and shapes in regular color images) and return a label for the whole image, or (more interestingly) one label for each pixel in the image, creating a dense habitat map of the coral reef seafloor.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-fusion-800 wp-image-3667" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-800x572.png" alt="" width="800" height="572" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-200x143.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-300x214.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-400x286.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-600x429.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-768x549.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden-800x572.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/evolution_mapping_bijgesneden.png 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1. Simplified evolution of underwater mapping methods and the results in each case.</em></p>
<p><b><br />
Adapting to the lack of field work</b></p>
<p>In my project we use a diver-operated device called the HyperDiver (HD), to acquire underwater hyperspectral images of coral reefs that are then used to produce detailed habitat maps. Hyperspectral images are like regular color images, but instead of capturing the usual 3 color bands (RGB) they capture many more (up to 400 with the HD) bands in the visible light range. The HD’s hyperspectral camera is a line-scanner, meaning that successive lines of 640 pixels wide are taken as the diver pushes the device forward, basically scanning the reef in long transects. The rich data in each transect supplies the ML algorithm with around 130 times more spectral information to identify targets in the images, instead of relying only on textures and shapes. This allows the ML to predict detailed labels for each pixel in the image, for example organisms can be recognized down to species level and different substrate types can be differentiated (turf algae, sediment, cyanobacterial mat).</p>
<p>We developed a whole pipeline to produce these detailed habitat maps with ML algorithms from HD data. And since we have not been able to reach Indonesia, we tested our workflow with a “pre-pandemic” dataset, acquired in the Caribbean island of Curacao in 2016 by my supervisor Arjun Chennu. We found that the workflow produces accurate habitat maps from the images of coral reefs. I am currently working on describing the habitat structure and the biodiversity of the coral reefs of Curacao using these maps. Despite the great accuracy of the maps, one methodological caveat in the acquisition of the transects still remains. Namely that the transects form a barred grid of the reef with a one meter gap between each two parallel transects to reduce the redundancy produced by the overlap of the transects. This would be no issue if the transect images could be stitched together, but (because of methodological issues) this is not so straightforward. To solve this problem we have now expanded the HyperDiver’s imaging arsenal to capture color images that can be stitched together to produce orthomosaics, and then register the hyperspectral images on top of them.</p>
<p><em><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-fusion-800 wp-image-3654" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-800x256.png" alt="" width="800" height="256" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-200x64.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-300x96.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-400x128.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-600x192.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-768x245.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3-800x256.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure3.png 967w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><br />
Figure 2. Example section from a transect’s habitat map from the Curacao dataset. Corals (yellow, orange and pink), macroalgae (light and dark green), turf algae (olive), sediment (cream), sponges (blue), coralline algae (red) and even cyanobacterial mat (purple) are accurately classified in the hyperspectral transect.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3651" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-800x726.png" alt="" width="288" height="261" srcset="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-200x182.png 200w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-300x272.png 300w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-400x363.png 400w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-600x545.png 600w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-768x697.png 768w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast-800x726.png 800w, /4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure4__aangepast.png 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 288px) 100vw, 288px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3. Orthomosaic of &#8220;plastic corals&#8221; at the warehouse at the MPIMM. The orthomosaic was created using structure-from-motion software on images from the new color cameras added to the HyperDiver.</em></p>
<p>We have equipped two ‘point-and-shoot’ color cameras on the exterior of the HD, facing down in slightly different angles. The images from these cameras will produce the basis to build an orthomosaic of the scene. Since testing the device in the field was not possible so far, we tried the new setting on dry land. For this purpose we found some materials in the warehouse of the Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology (where I am based) and laid them on the ground of a large rectangular space (around 10&#215;10 meters). We then lifted the HD with a crane and simulated a dive, pushing it around and over our ‘plastic coral reef’. I had envisioned my first test of the HD in a completely different setting, but nonetheless I found it was a good introduction. Handling three devices (HyperDiver + 2 external cameras) was not easy, and doing it in a calm (and dry!) setting helped me get used to all the quirks of the process. After scanning the warehouse-floor, I downloaded all the images from the 3 devices and built the very first HD orthomosaic. I am looking forward to trying the HD underwater and capturing the first ‘wet’ orthomosaic with it.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3501" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/figure5.gif" alt="" width="632" height="406" /><br />
<em><br />
Figure 4. When you cannot reach your field work site, scan plastic corals at your institute!</em></p>
<p>We keep on developing the HD capabilities and have recently added a new multispectral camera to its camera inventory; I will write about this in a future post. Finally, I am thankful for the help from everybody involved in the project, which has made it possible to adapt to the obstacles posed by a global pandemic and its consequences.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/4D-REEF/wp-content/uploads/Daniel-Christoph-Schurholz-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-1-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/4D-REEF/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2726"><span class="esr-link">Daniel Christoph Schürholz</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Computer Science</p>
	<p>Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, Germany</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
