<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Max Fursman &#8211; 4D-REEF</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/max-fursman/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Past, present, and future of  coral reefs in the Coral Triangle</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 15:01:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Max at the 6th International Sclerochronology Conference</title>
		<link>/isc/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 14:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fursman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3978</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Max Fursman, based at Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany   The scientific community is a vibrant tapestry of intellect, curiosity, and collaboration that spans across borders and unites researchers from all corners of the world. Among the myriad of scientific events that showcase this international camaraderie is the International Sclerochronology Conference. The]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Blog by 4D-Reef ESR Max Fursman, based at Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The scientific community is a vibrant tapestry of intellect, curiosity, and collaboration that spans across borders and unites researchers from all corners of the world. Among the myriad of scientific events that showcase this international camaraderie is the International Sclerochronology Conference.<br />
The 6<sup>th</sup> ISC took place in Tokyo, Japan in May this year, as scientists from all over the globe either travelled or attended virtually to discuss all things sclerchronological (study of physical and chemical variations in the accretionary hard tissues of organisms).</p>
<p>I was representing 4D-Reef and Tridacna.</p>
<p>Usually the conference is held every 3 years but thanks to the pandemic the 6<sup>th</sup> sessions, which was due to take place in May 2022, was postponed by a year and a student run online conference was run instead.</p>
<p>After 19 hours and forty minutes of travel, or in other terms: 5 imodium-laced microwave-heated meals; 4 movies I had missed in cinemas; 3 hours of napping on a bench in Taipei airport cradling my laptop like a cabbage patch doll, I touched down in the Land of the Rising Sun.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3984" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture1.png" alt="" width="624" height="311" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture1-200x100.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture1-300x150.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture1-400x199.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture1-600x299.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture1-768x383.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture1.png 780w" sizes="(max-width: 624px) 100vw, 624px" /></p>
<p>I ate about a year’s worth of ramen in the few days before the conference…</p>
<p>The conference took place at the Hongo campus of the University of Tokyo, where in 1925 Prof. Hidesaburō Ueno died while lecturing. His loyal Akita dog Hachikō, who had learnt to wait for his owner to return at Shinuya station every day, continued to go and wait every day after his owner failed to return for nine years until he himself died… (Pass me the tissues)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3985" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture2.png" alt="" width="615" height="491" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture2-177x142.png 177w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-200x160.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-300x240.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-400x320.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-600x479.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-768x614.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2-800x639.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture2.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 615px) 100vw, 615px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left: The banner proudly guiding us to the Yayoi Auditorium</em><br />
<em>Right – Top: Hongo Campus, University of Tokyo</em><br />
<em>Right – Bottom: the heartbreaking statue of Prof. Ueno and Hachikō</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Hats off to the organising committee, let by Dr. Kotaro Shirai, as they did a truly superb job right from the get go.</p>
<p>Sunday evening we were welcomed to the meeting with an ice-breaker event where they had really pulled out all the stops. We were served a buffet of Japanese food, with opportunities to eat more mochi than the human body really should, sample Japanese wines and beers and were entertained by final year music students in what turned out to be a very entertaining, though somewhat cramped, evening that settled everyone comfortably in for the week.</p>
<p>The conference itself was a stupendous and ran smooth as silk.<br />
The talks were a mixture of in person talks with some speakers joining via zoom from other countries, and covered topics from in depth sclerochemical analysis in fossil samples, to anthropology studies on shell remains in ancient middens.<br />
Some of the keynote talks on biomineralisation, sclera-proxy development and evolutionary paleobiology were especially interesting. One in particular, delivered by Prof. Burchell from Memorial University’s Department of Archaeology, was thought provoking and resonated with a lot of those assembled. Entitled “Imagining a Radical Future for Archaeology and Sclerochronology”, the talk focused on the use of Indigenous and native groups to regions that are used for research or sample collection, and how their input into the studies should be taken on board and the culture and traditions respected and included as part of our work. It left a lot to think about and prompted some healthy discussion during the next break.</p>
<p>Speaking of, the coffee breaks were held in the poster area and yet again Kotaro et al came through with a variety of Japanese cakes and snacks available to sample and gorge on!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3986" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture3.png" alt="" width="693" height="554" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture3-177x142.png 177w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-200x160.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-300x240.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-400x320.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-600x479.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-768x614.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3-800x639.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture3.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 693px) 100vw, 693px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left – top: The crowded ice-breaker event, with food galore and drinks flowing! </em><br />
<em>Left – bottom: the final day group photo!</em><br />
<em>Right – top: One very handsome sclerochronologist presenting his work on Tridacna  sclerochemistry, representing 4D-Reef</em><br />
<em>Right – bottom: musicians playing for us during the ice-breaker</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I was excited to present on my research, and spoke on a topic I had presented at ICRS last July, a long-term study into induced-seasonality in a tridacna sample. Since ICRS we have been able to expand our work into a greater depth and understanding and the chance to discuss it at a niche and specific conference where others would have intimate knowledge on the topic was a great opportunity. Myself and several others who study tridacna gathered afterwards to discuss our own work in depth and have since kept in contact and formed a slack group to trade ideas and promote further discourse on our sclerochemical endevours. While the virtual student ISC last September was interesting and engaging, the in person nature of a conference is something that cannot be replicated. These exchanges with people engaged in similar veins of work, and even those engaged in more general sclera-studies, have offered a chance to open up new avenues for collaboration and expanded my understanding of sclerochronology from various perspectives. The global nature of the conference facilitated interactions with scholars from different countries, fostering an enriching environment of cultural diversity and intellectual exchange.</p>
<p>Another treat organised by Kotaro et al was the conference dinner, which was a stupendous affair.</p>
<p>Held high up in Royal Park Hotel Tokyo we were treated to a buffet banquet overlooking Tokyo at night. Traditional foods, as well as Sake and beer, seemed to be in endless supply, with a tempura cooking display churning out fresh delicious snacks all evening.<br />
The evening ended with a wonderful recital of traditional music on koto, the national instrument of Japan. It was mesmerizing to watch the skill and deft movements needed to pluck and tune this instrument and to charm such sweet melodies out.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3987" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture4.png" alt="" width="627" height="501" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture4-177x142.png 177w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-200x160.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-300x240.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-400x320.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-600x479.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-768x614.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4-800x639.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture4.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left &#8211; top: The musicians playing the traditional koto for us in a beautiful demonstration.<br />
</em><em>Left – bottom: a group of scientists standing round enjoying the food and drinks, one in particular wearing a VERY fetching batik shirt…<br />
</em><em>Right – top: the group photo following the meal<br />
</em><em>Right – bottom: the view from the dining room overlooking Tokyo at night</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Beyond the confines of the conference halls, Tokyo unfolded as a captivating tapestry of cultural splendor. Each moment spent in the city was a sensory delight, offering an array of experiences that seamlessly blended ancient traditions with modern marvels. Any street could have simultaneously modern skyscrapers and stores, yet nestled within it is an untouched temple where the noise and bustle of the city seems to melt away. I found myself enthralled by the harmonious coexistence of serenity and dynamism that defined Tokyo.<br />
We took our time to immerse ourselves in this new place, visiting temples, tourist attractions and trying our hand at karaoke!<br />
One absolute highlight was a trip we took out to the coastal town of Enoshima, and the island just off the coast. Far from there, standing on the skyline, was the snow-capped peak of Mt. Fuji, piercing the sky with its grandeur. A slight fog added a mystic, ethereal haze to the scene, and the sheer beauty of the mountain seared itself into my mind.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3988" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture5.png" alt="" width="581" height="464" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture5-177x142.png 177w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-200x160.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-300x240.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-400x320.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-600x479.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-768x614.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5-800x639.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture5.png 975w" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Left –top: Me in front of Sensō-ji temple, Tokyo<br />
</em><em>Left – bottom: Iris finding Tridacna for sale at the beach. Sadly CITES might have taken issue to putting it in our carry-on…<br />
</em><em>Middle – top: Up in the hills at Kiyomizu-dera temple, Kyoto<br />
</em><em>Middle – middle: Inside the Torii tunnel on the mountain of Fushimi Inari-Taisha shrine<br />
</em><em>Middle – bottom: Mt. Fuji through the clouds, across the bay from Enoshima Island<br />
</em><em>Right – top: Meeting a celebrity at the Studio Ghibli shop (ignore the socks and shorts)<br />
</em><em>Right – bottom – quietly enjoying costume karaoke with my fellow conference attendees</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>What truly was a treat though, was Tokyo&#8217;s culinary scene. It proved to be a delight for the senses and I indulged in what can only be described as a gastronomic adventure in my spare time. Ramen, sushi, tempura, gyoza, I tried anything and everything I could. Some of it was unusual, such as the konjac, or devil’s tongue potato, which proved to have a tasty but fat/gelatin-like consistency when stewed. But everything was delicious and there is not one item I wouldn’t order again in a heartbeat.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3989" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture6.png" alt="" width="368" height="520" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture6-200x283.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture6-212x300.png 212w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture6-400x565.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture6.png 510w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>A sampling of the food consumed on this trip</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Overall, the journey from Frankfurt to Tokyo for the 6th International Sclerochronology Conference was an extraordinary experience that blended scientific exploration with cultural immersion. The conference itself proved to be a hub of knowledge, where ideas flowed freely, collaborations flourished, and new contacts made.<br />
Beyond the academic sphere, Tokyo&#8217;s vibrant culture, awe-inspiring landmarks, and culinary wonders created a tapestry of experiences that left an indelible mark on my journey.</p>
<p>From presenting my research findings to engaging in stimulating discussions with experts in the field, I felt the conference fostered personal and professional growth. Tokyo, with its harmonious blend of tradition and innovation, captivated my senses, offering a glimpse into the rich cultural heritage of Japan, and I am grateful for the opportunities to learn, connect, and explore.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3990" src="/wp-content/uploads/Picture7.jpg" alt="" width="276" height="207" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Picture7-200x150.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture7-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture7-400x300.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Picture7.jpg 532w" sizes="(max-width: 276px) 100vw, 276px" /></p>
<p style="font-weight: 400; text-align: center;"><em>Sunset behind the main entrance Torii (sacred arch at shrine/temple entrances) at Fushimi Inari-Taisha shrine</em></p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Max-Fursman-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2743"><span class="esr-link">Max Fursman</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy and Biodiversity</p>
	<p>Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>4D-Reef at the 15th International Coral Reef Symposium</title>
		<link>/4d-reef-at-the-15th-international-coral-reef-symposium/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 13:18:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leonardo Bertini]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fursman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3697</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Where do we even begin, it's the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where do we even begin, it&#8217;s the largest gathering of reef minds on Earth, the International Coral Reef Symposium! (ICRS for those of you in the know). Naturally, the story of a massive event like that deserves 2 of the most talkative creatures on Earth (i.e., the authors of this blogpost) aaaaand a cornetfish-long blog post. (For those clueless about our awful joke see Fig. 1c; self-explanatory hopefully &#x1f605;?). This event was also the first ever climate neutral ICRS. Anyway, strap in and prepare to hear about how we schooled (another reef joke!!) for a week with fellow reef enthusiasts in the charming city of Bremen, northern Germany.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3708 " src="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png" alt="" width="382" height="554" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-200x290.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-207x300.png 207w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-400x579.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-600x869.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-707x1024.png 707w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1-768x1112.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo1.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1: <strong>a):</strong> The “Town Musicians of Bremen” &#8211; a Grimm’s fairy tale about a group of aging animals who move to Bremen to become musicians and their stack is an unofficial symbol of the city. <strong>b): </strong>The opening ceremony of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS. <strong>c)</strong> A blue-spotted cornet fish (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fistularia_commersonii">Fistularia commersonii)</a>.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>ICRS usually happens every four years and, after the 2021 edition was turned into a virtual meeting due to the pandemic, the wilds of humanity descended upon the delayed in-person event in order to (while following all health and safety protocols) socialise and discuss all things reef! This cosmopolitan single event had more than 1500 attendees coming from more than 170 countries across the globe, joining online and in-person. 4D-Reef was well represented, coming from across Europe to join with our endemic Bremenites who were helping to organise the event.</p>
<p>Those Bremen-based 4D-Reefers present were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Daniel Schürholz (Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Arjun Chennu (Max-Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, MPI)</li>
<li>Estradivari (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Sebastian Ferse (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
<li>Kathrine Maxwell (Leibniz Centre for Tropical Marine Research, ZMT)</li>
</ul>
<p>Honestly, each one of them deserves their own round of applause and their own blog post for that matter, as they have been central to the organisation and success of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS and all behind-the-scenes perks. To all the Bremen 4D-Reefers, we would like to express our gratitude and admiration on behalf of all our colleagues. They have gone to extreme lengths, chaired sessions, organised side events, led visits to their institutes and on top of all that also presented their own research at ICRS. Hats off to you guys!!</p>
<p>The 4D reef delegation was not just composed of endemic folks. We had a significant representation of 4D-Reefers from all over the place who made their way to Bremen to give either poster or oral presentations (check the official tweet from 4D-Reef and the various threads for more deets and super dooper sciency pics and embarrassing moments too &#8211; yeah there was a party in the end and yeah we shook it all off till we bleached). As part of the visiting delegation, we had:</p>
<ul>
<li>Leo Bertini (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Bristol)</li>
<li>Max Fursman (Goethe University Frankfurt)</li>
<li>Andrew Torres (The Natural History Museum &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
<li>Kenneth Johnson (The Natural History Museum)</li>
<li>Erica Hendy (University of Bristol)</li>
<li>William Harrison (Naturalis Biodiversity Centre &amp; University of Amsterdam)</li>
</ul>
<p>If you&#8217;d like to have a glimpse at what each of them have been up to, please check out the <a href="https://www.icrs2022.de/fileadmin/user_upload/ICRS2022_BookOfAbstracts_July2.pdf">Official Conference Book of Abstracts</a> by searching their names.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-3721 size-fusion-800" src="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png" alt="" width="800" height="405" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-200x101.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-300x152.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-400x203.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-540x272.png 540w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-600x304.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-768x389.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2-800x405.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo2.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2: All the 4D-Reef PhDs hard at work, presenting posters, talks and their equipment.</em><br />
<em><strong><u>Top row</u></strong><u>:</u>  <strong>Daniel</strong> proudly stands next to his Hyper Diver holding up the information posters, waiting to ambush anyone passing by and tell them all about the wonderous imaging that can be done.<strong> Andrew</strong> gleefully discusses his work at his poster during the poster sessions, enthralling a passer-by with his knowledge. <strong><u>Middle row</u></strong>:<strong> Kat</strong> dazzles the crowd with her talk on coral reef terraces, scattering pictures of her fieldwork in the Philippines throughout to make us jealous! <strong>Estra </strong>educates everyone on MPAs and the emergence of OECMs and their benefits. <strong>Max </strong>doesn’t clam up as he discusses Tridacna shell chemistry! <strong><u>Bottom row</u></strong>: <strong>Leo </strong>has captured a CT lover and is busy discussing the ins and outs of coral scanning. <strong>Will </strong>wows those nearby with his remarks on changing coral reef habitats.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Face to face is important: strengthening connections and accelerating collabs</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a fantastic opportunity for us to present our work to the reef community, and many of the 4D-Reefers had posters and talks at the conference. It was such a nice change of pace to be able to chat to people face to face about science and answer questions from them over a second glass of wine or third bagel. Some of us got to meet up with colleagues from previous endeavours, be it our masters or other research projects. But more importantly got to meet new people, discuss new ideas for research and potential collaborations. We were able to expand our network through our current peers, including friends we’ve been working in close collaboration with from Cardiff University, Imperial College London, Malaysia, Singapore and Frankfurt, as they acted as match makers and introduced us to their own networks.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3710 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png" alt="" width="566" height="471" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-200x167.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-300x250.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-400x333.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-600x500.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-768x640.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3-800x666.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo3.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3: Leo reuniting with and meeting new people.<strong> a)</strong> Dear friends Catie, Dom Brown and Luigi whom I worked with during my MSc looking at how reefs in Chagos have endured since the 2015 mass bleaching event. <strong>b)</strong> A fellow Brazilian ICRS attendee, Gabriel Cardoso, a PhD at Frei University Berlin looking at coral geochemical records. I met Gabriel in person after having read from his latest and outstanding work investigating how reefs in the Abrolhos bank were impacted by turbidity caused by mining refuse following the collapse of the Fundão dam, considered the biggest environmental disaster in Brazilian history, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969721059581">more here</a>. <strong>c) </strong>A prosecco with Sara Todorovic by my poster. Sara and her supervisor Dr Henry Wu, from ZMT, have been my collaborators. They look at geochemical signatures in coral cores from which I am automating the retrieval of growth rates and coral endobiont metrics.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3711 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png" alt="" width="560" height="563" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-66x66.png 66w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-150x150.png 150w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-200x201.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-400x402.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-600x603.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4-768x772.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo4.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4: Social gatherings. <strong>a and</strong> <strong>d) </strong>The members of 4D-Reef and associates gathered for a beer and food after a hard day of conferencing! <strong>b)</strong> Allia Rosedy, our Malaysian associate, munching on a pretzel tree. <strong>c)</strong> Polyp Leo overheating and expelling his zooxanthellae while showing his moves to the beat of ABBA. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>The first climate neutral ICRS ever</strong><br />
Given how our reefs have been suffering in the face of anthropogenic pressures, the least we can do to halt global warming is to try and minimize our everyday carbon footprints and this was the mindset behind every single aspect of the 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS.</p>
<p>For instance, attendees were given free public transport around town, thus encouraging a greener way of mass mobility (our badges acted as public transport passes – how clever of you people!). When it comes to food during either coffee breaks or lunches, catering was also well thought-out and vegetarian (we, being a Brazilian and an Irish, were suspicious of this, given our white-tip-shark-like instincts for blood – another reef joke, it’s been a while). But honestly, food was so outstandingly tasty that we welcomed the menu like sea anemones welcome clown fish.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-fusion-200 wp-image-3712 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="141" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-200x141.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-300x212.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-400x283.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-600x424.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-768x543.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5-800x565.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/maxleo5.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 5: Post-lunch break in the ICRS poster lounge. That was the best place to chill and recover from our food comas after lunch (left to right: Max, Leo and Andrew- not so satiated apparently?).</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Another striking aspect from catering was that priority was given for seasonal and local produce and the next day’s menu included ingredients used the day before to reduce food waste. Speaking of waste, this year there was rarely a flyer or physical promotional goodies around (let’s be honest those often end up forgotten in drawers). The entire programme was available to attendees via a web application, with real time announcements, chat, polling, and social functionalities. Attendees were also encouraged to bring their own liquid containers for drinking water and paper cups were offered as a better alternative to plastic.</p>
<p>Of course, it is impossible to actively reduce our carbon footprint to zero over such a short amount of time. There were energy costs for ventilating the venue, electricity, participant overseas travel emissions and other essentials that we cannot give up on (after all, we will never be as resourceful and energy efficient as corals). For this, organisers used part of the fees to purchase carbon credits equivalent of 1.491 tons of carbon emissions. The purchase is regulated by a third company who ensures measures are put into place to neutralize our carbon footprints following the UN environment programme and the Kyoto protocol.</p>
<p><strong>Our retrospective</strong></p>
<p>ICRS was a wonderful opportunity to not only showcase the incredible work we’ve been doing as part of 4D-Reef and to bring awareness of how important turbid reefs are, but also to get new perspectives and connect with an amazing swarm of both young and well-established scientists from across multiple fields.</p>
<p>The conference was an opportunity to celebrate our endurance over the hardship the pandemic has brought onto the community, both as a whole and for some at deeply personal levels. Throughout the event, we shared (and vented – because we’re all human) about how we managed to stay afloat through such murky times. There was a moment to remember all the loved ones we lost along the way since the last in-person ICRS. May we continue their legacy and make the remaining reefs proud of what we do to protect the oceans!</p>
<p>The 15<sup>th</sup> ICRS has definitely set the bar high for any upcoming conferences. We already look forward to the ingenuity that will come with the 16<sup>th</sup> ICRS, which will be in New Zealand (i.e., land of Erica, land of the kiwis and the Maori).</p>
<p>Ka kite ano, ICRS!</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Max-Fursman-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2743"><span class="esr-link">Max Fursman</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy and Biodiversity</p>
	<p>Goethe University Frankfurt, Germany</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Leonardo-Bertini-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2735"><span class="esr-link">Leonardo Bertini</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Biological Resources</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
