<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>4D-REEF update &#8211; 4D-REEF</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/update/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Past, present, and future of  coral reefs in the Coral Triangle</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 13:31:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Scientific Dive Course Part 2: Electric Boogaloo</title>
		<link>/scientific-dive-course-part-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 12:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3674</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“Tam” Towels on the dive course. This is what we call surfing towels after 4D-REEF team member Tamara Stuij. Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.   Blog by Mike Hynes, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center.   We survived! After a very intense three weeks, working weekends and late into the evening, I am]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“Tam” Towels on the dive course. This is what we call surfing towels after 4D-REEF team member Tamara Stuij. Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.  </em></p>
<p><em>Blog by Mike Hynes, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We survived! After a very intense three weeks, working weekends and late into the evening, I am happy to report that Flo-D REEF (4D-REEF and our fellow dive course member Flo, who works on super cool fish from the Caribbean called hamlets. Also I am hoping my new underwater symbol for hamlets catches on) have all passed the European Scientific Dive Course (German Edition run by our consortium affiliate institution ZMT, more info <a href="https://www.leibniz-zmt.de/en/research-infrastructure/scientific-diving-centre.html">here</a>). Though some of us still need to get a lifeguard certificate before receiving the official Scientific Certification, but that’s just a formality (I hope. Fingers crossed). Los Gigantes, Tenerife in the Canary Islands was the home of our latest 4D-REEF adventure.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3683" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2.png" alt="" width="844" height="419" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-200x99.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-300x149.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-400x199.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-600x298.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-768x381.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2-800x397.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-1_formfit_lower2.png 844w" sizes="(max-width: 844px) 100vw, 844px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1 – All of us on the boat ready to practice the swim test. Image courtesy of Andreas Kunzmann.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I will not lie, this course was difficult (like real difficult. Far surpassing any of my previous dive courses, including my Dive Master), full of paperwork and homework (to the German standards of course), and despite a lot of last minute organization, we managed to get the most out of it. In no small part because we got to go to sunny and beautiful Tenerife. Here we learned important skills like dive operation planning and teamwork: adequately assessing risks, mitigating them, and devising a strategy to quickly and safely conduct our underwater research. Safety and rescue drills galore were done to prepare us to deal with a variety of issues that can happen to divers (such as entanglements, heart attacks, decompression illness, and more).  And we even got to test out a cool scientific method called the Hyper Diver (stay tuned to learn about this). We also had an opportunity to bond (something about the bonding power of shared suffering or something like that) and spend time together as (part of) the consortium, something that has been lacking due to corona and travel restrictions. This is evident as even after 3 weeks of diving, most of us went on a fun dive to just enjoy diving together (and a reward for all our hard work). Well, that and we wanted to check out some of the other dive sites on the island that we didn’t have a chance to get to on the course (not that Octopus Cove wasn’t a nice spot, but after 3 weeks of only diving there, a different set of scenery was appreciated).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3678" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="637" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-200x150.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-400x300.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-600x450.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit-800x600.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_formfit.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2 – Five of us on a fun dive after we passed the exam. Image courtesy of Andrew Torres.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Now to the science part. We had to do a scientific project whilst diving as part of the course. I mentioned the Hyper Diver earlier and it is a cool tool that is being used by one of our ESR’s, Daniel Schürholz. Meeting at La Paella Rustica (NOT Daniel’s favorite restaurant) we learned all about this cool technique. Daniel then trusted us with a piece of equipment worth more than everything I own (but Daniel loves me enough to trust me, and I guess the others too).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3696" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit.png" alt="" width="840" height="354" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-200x84.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-300x126.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-400x169.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-600x253.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-768x324.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit-800x337.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_formfit.png 840w" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3 – Left: Dino Ramos using the Hyper Diver, therefore becoming ‘Hyper Dino’. Image courtesy of </em><em>Daniel Schürholz and Estradivari. Right: The supermarket chain in The Canaries ALSO named Hiperdino </em><em>(And which we are certain our Dino makes money from, but he still wouldn’t give us a discount). Image </em><em>courtesy of Hiperdino’s webpage.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>So I won’t get too bogged down into details as I know Daniel has recently written a <a href="/coral-reef-habitat-mapping-in-corona-times">blog</a> explaining this WAAAYYY better than I ever could. Ostensibly, the Hyper Diver has 4 cameras, 2 standard RGB cameras and 2 cameras that are hyperspectral/multispectral (capturing more wavelengths then we can see with the human eye). There are also sensors like depth, altitude, light, pH, and more, to help calibrate the images being created. I am sure Daniel is internally screaming at me for saying something wrong, but basically we do this to create 3D topography images of the sea floor, and also to determine what animal communities/species are present. So by all of us doing this we have helped Daniel collect some data for his project from a new region with different organisms living here. And by having so many different operators, he can assess if repeatability between users is at a good level. So another useful output from our diving course has been the use of the Hyper Diver, and its data.<img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3501" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-4-1-1.gif" alt="" width="632" height="406" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4 – A 3D topographic model produced in Tenerife of the sea floor using Hyper Diver iamges. </em><em>Image courtesy of Daniel Schürholz.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Finally, thanks to the <a href="https://www.divingtenerife.co.uk/">diveshop </a>and its staff (Shiela, Paul, Sam, Neville, Chris, and Josh) for helping us through this course and taking us on a fun dive. Also, I would be remiss if I didn’t mention our favorite places that made Los Gigantes a great time; Berry’s ice cream (the guanábana ice cream was the best flavor. Don’t @ me), La Sangria, of course La Paella Rustica, and Highland Paddy’s (home of nightly karaoke and the ‘One Woman Band’ Solange. Incredible night. You had to be there. Trust me).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3680" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit.jpg" alt="" width="849" height="637" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-200x150.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-400x300.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-600x450.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit-800x600.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_formfit.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /><br />
<em>Figure 5 – Having a lovely dinner at La Paella Rustica before Daniel takes his expensive Hyper Diver away from us (for good reasons). Image courtesy of Dino Ramos.</em></p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Carboneras Network Training Activity 2.0</title>
		<link>/carboneras-nta-2-0/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 08:40:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Network Activities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NTA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Harrison]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3585</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By William Harrison, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center.   From April 20th to 24th, 2020 February 20th through 26th 2022, the 4D-REEF consortium met once again. And this time we actually went to Spain! In person! Where better to launch an old-fashioned, in-person event than a hotel made out of sets of]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>By William Harrison, PhD student of 4D-REEF at Naturalis Biodiversity Center. </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>From <del datetime="2022-03-21T08:58:34+00:00">April 20th to 24th, 2020 </del>February 20th through 26th 2022, the 4D-REEF consortium met once again. And this time we actually went to Spain! In person! Where better to launch an old-fashioned, in-person event than a hotel made out of sets of old movies? The grand Hotel El Dorado, in Carboneras, Spain provided a fantastic base of operations for our daily expeditions; starting around 8:30 we would pile onto the group bus and head wherever Juan Carlos led us. And as a professor from the University of Granada who has been working in the region so long that he wrote the information signs at some of our stops, Juan Carlos knew where to lead.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3618" src="/wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2.png" alt="" width="760" height="441" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-200x116.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-300x174.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-400x232.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-600x348.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-768x446.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2-800x465.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Afbeelding1_achtergrond-weg2.png 930w" sizes="(max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 1: A gorgeous sunrise greeted us every morning. (Left &#8211; Photo credit Andrew Torres). Map of Spain, with Carboneras marked (Right &#8211; Image credit Google Maps)</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We did not need expert advice to see that the views were breathtaking, but Juan Carlos opened our eyes to the hills’ hidden histories. Under his guidance, a gently sloping hill became a talus slope, slight changes in the color of rocks became shallowing and re-flooding trends, and ancient coral reefs were suddenly everywhere!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3589" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden.jpg" alt="" width="763" height="508" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-200x133.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-400x267.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden-800x533.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-2_bijgesneden.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 763px) 100vw, 763px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 2: Juan Carlos with his ducklings in a row. The rocks under our feet represent a deepening upward sequence and were full of bivalves and brachiopods. (Photo credit Daniel Schürholz)</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-3623" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-1024x285.png" alt="" width="1024" height="285" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-200x56.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-300x83.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-400x111.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-600x167.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-768x214.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-800x223.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-1024x285.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-1200x334.png 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2-1536x427.png 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-3_bijgesneden2.png 6000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 3: ESRs enjoy the scenery visible from atop a Miocene coral reef.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Yes, you read that correctly! Southern Spain used to have coral reefs. Now, I know how it is. When you hear a geologist say something ‘used to have’ something, you think “oh, this is one of those crazy geologist with no sense of time talking about when Spain ‘used to have’ dinosaurs”. But these reefs are barely 5 million years young! OK, maybe I am a crazy geologist with no sense of time, but 5 million years is nothing in geological time; why, the first hominids had already appeared by then! Back then, the Mediterranean waters around Spain were filled with corals and other reef taxa. Sadly, the entire Mediterranean dried up in the end of the Miocene; while it did re-flood in the Pliocene, all the reef corals had gone extinct and none of the waters connected to the Mediterranean had any corals to recolonize the Spanish coastline. The dead reefs were buried by later sediments and eventually dissolved since coral shells are made of unstable aragonite. Today they are preserved as casts of corals filled with more stable materials and caves where now-dissolved reefs used to reside.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3591" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-4.png" alt="" width="479" height="638" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-4-200x267.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-4-225x300.png 225w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-4-400x533.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-4.png 535w" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 100vw, 479px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 4: Coral reefs were abundant in the Mediterranean during the Miocene. Here you can see A) a coral reef with corals preserved as columns and a cave left by dissolved material below and B) a remarkably accurate cast of a coral colony. (Photo credit Daniel Schürholz)</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The most interesting taxa besides corals were, in my unbiased opinion as a foraminifera researcher, the foraminifera. These single-celled amoeba-like protists built lentil-sized shells to live in. Like corals, they enjoy living in warm water and thrive in well-lit conditions where they can farm photosynthetic algae. Unlike corals, they used stable calcite, so they are nicely preserved for us to find and study. Much prettier to look at!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3592" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden.jpg" alt="" width="761" height="507" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-200x133.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-400x267.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden-800x533.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-5_bijgesneden.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 5: Foraminifera, kings of algae. Each lentil-shaped grain in this picture is the shell of a single-celled alga. (Photo Credit Dino Ramos)</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>All in all a great (and educational) time was had by all. But wait, there’s more to this trip than fieldwork! Wednesday we took a break from hiking to socialize and to plan. To plot. To scheme together and find opportunities for collaborations between ESRs. The day started with ESR project speed-dating, in which all 15 ESRs spent 5 minutes with each of the other ESRs discussing our projects and looking for places where they overlap. Then we moved to prearranged groups talking about pre-planned projects; ESRs who did not have a project to discuss planned to shoot a short film.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-3593 alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden.png" alt="" width="761" height="507" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-200x133.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-300x200.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-400x267.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-600x400.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-768x512.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden-800x533.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-6_bijgesneden.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 6: Mike G. Hynes deals with paparazzi as he films his breakout role. (Photo credit Daniel Schürholz)</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>All in all a good time was had by everyone. Sadly, this journey had to come to a close. After eating together and exploring the reefs of Spain as a group, we had to part ways once more. Hopefully these discussions will bear many fruits and I look forward to seeing the completed film. Next time in Indonesia!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3594" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden.png" alt="" width="764" height="509" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-200x133.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-300x200.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-400x267.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-600x400.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-768x512.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden-800x533.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/Figure-7_bijgesneden.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 764px) 100vw, 764px" /></p>
<p><em>Figure 7: After eating together and exploring the reefs of Spain as a group, we had to part ways once more. Hopefully we will meet again this summer in Indonesia! (Photo credit Daniel Schürholz)</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div style="width: 720px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-3585-1" width="720" height="1280" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-8_Trim.mp4?_=1" /><a href="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-8_Trim.mp4">/wp-content/uploads/Figure-8_Trim.mp4</a></video></div>
<p><em>Figure 8: We made many new friends in Spain with all sorts of numbers of legs but in the end we had to say goodbye. (Video credit Andrew Torres)</em></p>
<p>Until next time!</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/William-Harrison-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2402"><span class="esr-link">William Harrison</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Geosciences: Palaeobiology</p>
	<p>Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Netherlands</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="/wp-content/uploads/Figure-8_Trim.mp4" length="3929970" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stand with Ukraine</title>
		<link>/stand-with-ukraine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Cornelissen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3576</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We are absolutely shocked and horrified by the abhorrent actions of the Russian government against Ukraine. There are just no words. 4D-Reef stands for cooperation across borders, finding strength in our cultural differences, and the knowledge that we are stronger working together. One of our own early stage researchers is from Ukraine, currently living in]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are absolutely shocked and horrified by the abhorrent actions of the Russian government against Ukraine. There are just no words. 4D-Reef stands for cooperation across borders, finding strength in our cultural differences, and the knowledge that we are stronger working together.</p>
<p>One of our own early stage researchers is from Ukraine, currently living in the Netherlands for her research. The strength of her and her friends and family still in Ukraine is simply incredible.</p>
<p>If you want to help, but don’t know how, you could consider any of the following options:</p>
<p>1) Spreading awareness.</p>
<p>2) Join demonstrations in support of Ukraine in your cities.</p>
<p>3) Donate. Do your research and donate to an organization that will make the most of your donation. There are many local organizations active in Ukraine, as well as international organizations that have established special funds or are on the ground in and around Ukraine.</p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Estradivari co-authored an article in NATURE Comment</title>
		<link>/estradivari-co-authored-an-article-in-nature-comment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline van Impelen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 17:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our 4D-REEF researcher Estradivari co-authored a recently published article in NATURE Comment: Biodiversity needs every tool in the box: use OECMs Cited from the article: "To conserve global biodiversity, countries must forge equitable alliances that support sustainability in traditional pastoral lands, fisheries-management areas, Indigenous territories and more. Global support is growing for the 30 × 30 movement]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div>Our 4D-REEF researcher <a href="/esr/estradivari/">Estradivari </a>co-authored a recently published article in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02041-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02041-4&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1629714808415000&amp;usg=AFQjCNGiIoj9x6tEk-tCWMT8mMPPfxWeZw">NATURE Comment:</a></div>
<h3><em>Biodiversity needs every tool in the box: use OECMs</em></h3>
<p><em>Cited from the article: &#8220;To conserve global biodiversity, countries must forge equitable alliances that support sustainability in traditional pastoral lands, fisheries-management areas, Indigenous territories and more.</em></p>
<p>Global support is growing for the 30 × 30 movement — a goal to conserve 30% of the planet by 2030. In May, the G7 group of wealthy nations endorsed the commitment to this target that had been made by more than 50 countries in January. It is likely to be the headline goal when parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) meet to discuss the latest global conservation agreement in May 2022 in Kunming, China.</p>
<p>[..] OECMs could help to achieve the 30% target.&#8221;</p>
<div>Gurney GG, Darling ES, Ahmadia GN, Agostini VN, Ban NC, Blythe J, Claudet J, Epstein G, <strong>Estradivari</strong>, Himes-Cornell A, Jonas HD, Armitage A, Campbell SJ, Cox C, Friedman WR, Gill D, Lestari P, Mangubhai S, McLeod E, Muthiga NA, Naggea J, Ranaivoson R, Wenger A, Yulianto I, Jupiter SD (2021) Biodiversity needs every tool in the box: use OECMs. Nature comment.  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-021-02041-4">doi:10.1038/d41586-021-02041-4</a></div>
<p>This is a publication of the project she worked on before joining 4D-Reef.</p>
<div>WCS and WWF have issued a <a href="https://newsroom.wcs.org/News-Releases/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/16423/New-Nature-Comment-To-Advance-Equitable-and-Effective-Conservation-OECMs-Should-Be-a-Key-Policy-Tool-in-New-Global-Biodiversity-Agreement.aspx">WCS-press release</a> and a <a href="https://www.worldwildlife.org/press-releases/new-nature-comment-to-advance-equitable-and-effective-conservation-oecms-should-be-a-key-policy-tool-in-new-global-biodiversity-agreement">WWF press release</a></div>
<div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Surveying what’s hidden: using ARMS to capture cryptic biodiversity</title>
		<link>/arms-deployment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 08:49:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ESR blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Andrew Torres]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dedi Parenden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dino Angelo Ramos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fieldwork]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Dino Ramos (ESR 11 at University of Granada), Andrew Torres (ESR 3 at Natural History Museum London) and Dedi Parenden (ESR 17 at Hasanuddin University) COVID-19 has made working in the field still out of grasp for most of the ESRs and for many months we have all been longing for the day when]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Dino Ramos (ESR 11 at University of Granada), Andrew Torres (ESR 3 at Natural History Museum London) and Dedi Parenden (ESR 17 at Hasanuddin University)</span></i></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">COVID-19 has made working in the field still out of grasp for most of the ESRs and for many months we have all been longing for the day when we can dive into the warm waters of the tropics (Figure 1). While it is still too early to predict when we might be able to dip our toes into Spermonde’s not-so-crystal-clear waters, with our colleagues from Hasanuddin University (UNHAS) on-site, we can start setting up sampling devices to help address a very basic question: “What organisms can we find in these coral reefs?”. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3483" src="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig.jpg" alt="" width="645" height="484" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-200x150.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-400x300.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-600x450.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig-800x600.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 645px) 100vw, 645px" /></p>
<p>Figure 1. <span style="font-weight: 400;">Warm waters of the tropics. We’ll get there, buddy.</span></p>
<p><b>Invisible species richness</b><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It is a simple question, but not an easy one to answer. The Spermonde Archipelago is a well-studied area and ever since the days of exploration, scientists and naturalists have been cataloguing its diverse and colorful marine life. Located almost at the geographic heart of the Coral Triangle, one can surmise the sheer scale of biodiversity that this group of islands may contain. It is likely that most of the obvious (i.e. large and charismatic) flora and fauna have already been recorded. However, the diversity of coral reefs is also a function of the many nooks and crannies formed by their complex three-dimensional structure. These also happen to be where our microsnails and coralline algae are expected to be the most diverse. Common survey methods such as the underwater visual census do not necessarily include these hidden microhabitats. It can also be quite tricky to sample the shy organisms all cozied up in the corals without totally wrecking their homes apart. How then can we find out who resides in these mysterious, hard-to-reach spaces? We use our ARMS.</span></p>
<p><b>Artificial ‘hotels’ for reef creatures</b><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Autonomous Reef Monitoring Structures, or simply ARMS, are designed to simulate the cryptic spaces in coral reefs. They are made of stacked PVC plates (Figure 2) and fastened securely to the ocean floor amid coral reef habitats. Think of them as tiny apartelles for small marine life to check into. Each “floor” provides space for organisms to occupy. Floors alternately contain dividers to create either small rooms or larger floor spaces to settle onto. The longer these units are left in the ocean, the more ecological succession can take place to passively create different niches and accumulate more and more organisms (and organismal interactions!) through time (Figure 2c). These will represent at least part of the cryptic diversity present in the turbid reefs that we aim to investigate.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-3490" src="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2.png" alt="" width="782" height="440" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-200x113.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-400x225.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-600x338.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-768x432.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2-800x450.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig2.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 782px) 100vw, 782px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 2. a) Autonomous Reef Monitoring Structures (ARMS) schematics from NOAA; b) ARMS units constructed at the University of Hasanuddin (UNHAS) ready to be deployed (photo by Halwi Masdar); c) A potential recruitment outlook in ARMS after three years.</span></p>
<p><b>With a little bit of help from our Indonesian friends</b><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">4D-REEF has a great collaboration with researchers and students from UNHAS, which shows even more value in these difficult times when we are unable to travel from Europe to Indonesia ourselves to deploy these ARMS. Now the rainy season is over, a group of UNHAS students went into the field to deploy 18 ARMS at turbid coral reefs near 6 islands which range in levels of turbidity. The distance of each of the six islands to the mainland and Makassar city varies. Some are really close and can be reached in 10-15 minutes by using a local community boat, while the farthest location, Langkai Island, is about 2 hours by boat. The field team cannot visit all islands on the same day, so it takes 4-5 days to visit all the research locations.</span></p>
<p><b>DIY underwater </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">The team, consisting of 5 scuba divers, is working hard under water using hammers, stakes, wrenches, nuts and bolts, to install the ARMS (Figure 3). Data about the environment is collected at the same time as well as a range of water quality measures. Water temperature and light loggers are also installed at the research sites, which will give us more information about the variability of the water conditions over time. During the ARMS deployment, all loggers that were installed a few months ago were checked and reloaded. All activities ran smoothly and without obstacles, because of good preparations, fairly good weather conditions and quite calm seas. We will regularly check whether the ARMS are still in place, and continue to read out the logger data. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3491" src="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3.png" alt="" width="849" height="328" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-200x77.png 200w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-300x116.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-400x155.png 400w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-600x232.png 600w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-768x297.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3-800x309.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/ARMS-fig3.png 849w" sizes="(max-width: 849px) 100vw, 849px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure 3. Deployment of ARMS in the waters of the Spermonde Archipelago by our colleagues from UNHAS. The images clearly show the differences in turbidity between different sites.</span></p>
<p><b>Connecting to global efforts</b><br />
<span style="font-weight: 400;">The use of ARMS is a revolutionary way of capturing snapshots of reef biodiversity and how these are shaped by different environmental conditions. The dimensions of the ARMS units and its protocols are standardized according to the guidelines provided by the Global ARMS Program. So one of the many advantages to using ARMS is the comparisons we can make with the existing </span><a href="https://www.oceanarms.org/deployments/search"><span style="font-weight: 400;">network of ARMS projects</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Because of the reproducibility of ARMS, it allows us to contextualize our results on a much wider scale. And with the rapidly declining health of reefs around the world, it has become a very important and helpful tool to employ in understanding the complex ecology of our reef organisms. We are grateful that with the help from our Indonesian colleagues we can start collecting data despite not being able to travel to the field ourselves!</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>


<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Andrew-Torres-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2722"><span class="esr-link">Andrew Torres</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Science</p>
	<p>Natural History Museum, UK</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Dedi-Parenden-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2751"><span class="esr-link">Dedi Parenden</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Marine Management</p>
	<p>University of Hasanuddin, Indonesia</p></div>

<div class="esr-author">
	<img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/Dino-Angelo-Ramos-4D-REEF-early-stage-researcher-150x150.jpg" style="float:left;padding-right:30px;">
	<h3>Written by ESR: <a href="/?post_type=avada_portfolio#038;p=2739"><span class="esr-link">Dino Angelo Ramos</span></a> </h3> 
	<p>MSc in Taxonomy, Biodiversity and Evolution</p>
	<p>University of Granada, Spain</p></div>

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Willem Renema appointed Professor of Marine Palaeobiodiversity</title>
		<link>/willem-renema-appointed-professor-of-marine-palaeobiodiversity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 09:04:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3343</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Willem Renema, Project Coordinator of 4D-REEF, has been appointed professor by special appointment of Marine Palaeobiodiversity at the Faculty of Science of the University of Amsterdam (UvA). His Chair is hosted within the Department of Ecosystem &amp; Landscape Dynamics. Willem is combining the professorship with his position as research leader of Marine Biodiversity at Naturalis. This]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Willem Renema, Project Coordinator of 4D-REEF, has been <a href="https://ibed.uva.nl/shared/uva/en/news/professor-appointments/2020/10/willem-renema-appointed-professor-by-special-appointment-of-marine-palaeobiodiversity.html?origin=b2QFvrBwSRGQTONw78zjxw">appointed professor</a> by special appointment of Marine Palaeobiodiversity at the Faculty of Science of the University of Amsterdam (UvA). His Chair is hosted within the <a href="https://ibed.uva.nl/content/research-departments/eld/eld-department.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Department of Ecosystem &amp; Landscape Dynamics</a>. Willem is combining the professorship with his position as research leader of Marine Biodiversity at Naturalis.</p>
<p>This appointment strengthens the collaboration between Naturalis and UvA&#8217;s Institute for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Dynamics (IBED) in the field of palaeoecological research. Professor Renema is the promotor of five of the 4D-REEF Early Stage Researchers who are all hosted by UvA and jointly supervised by Naturalis and UvA staff.</p>
<p>Congratulations Willem with this appointment!</p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>4D-REEF pre-kick off meeting in Leiden</title>
		<link>/4d-reef-pre-kick-off-meeting/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chantal Huijbers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 09:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[4D-REEF update]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3079</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The 4D-REEF Consortium was awarded their EU Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions grant on Christmas Eve 2018. What a great news to start 2019 with the prospect of building a scientific hub of excellence in the relatively new domain of conservation palaeobiology. On 14 May 2019, the supervisory team convened for the first time in Leiden, the]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The 4D-REEF Consortium was awarded their EU Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions grant on Christmas Eve 2018. What a great news to start 2019 with the prospect of building a scientific hub of excellence in the relatively new domain of conservation palaeobiology.</p>
<p>On 14 May 2019, the supervisory team convened for the first time in Leiden, the Netherlands for a pre-kick-off meeting. Representatives from all beneficiaries and partner organisations attended the meeting. It was especially great to see a large representation from Indonesian counterparts in Leiden as well!</p>
<p>The agenda of the meeting included a general introduction of all beneficiaries and partners, recruitment procedures, financial arrangements, project planning including fieldwork and training activities, reporting and data management, risks, and an overview of the scientific programme.</p>
<p>The team is looking forward to recruiting a large cohort of 15 Early Stage Researchers plus three additional ESRs in Indonesia to increase our understanding of the role of turbid reefs for the future of marine ecosystems in the Coral Triangle as they respond to anthropogenic environmental change.</p>
<p><em>Participants of the 4D-REEF pre-kick off meeting (left to right): Newton Gomes, Dan Lunt, Sebastian Ferse, Elena Couce, Rohani Ambo Rappe, Juan Carlos Braga, Caroline van Impelen, Rita Dian Takarina, Owen Wangensteen, Erica Hendy, Jon Todd, Ocky Karna Rajasa, Gino Limmon, Hildegard Westphal, Peter Herman, Jamaluddin Jompa, Willem Renema, Alessio Rovere, Wolfgang Muller, Klemens Svetitsch, Miriam Schutter, Arjun Chennu, Luki Adirianto.</em></p>
 

]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
